<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Walwyns jvst defence against the aspertions cast upon him in a late un-Christian pamphlet entituled Walwyns wiles / by William Walwyn.</title>
            <author>Walwyn, William, 1600-1681.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 138 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67478</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W685</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27583</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09959961</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09959961</idno>
            <idno type="VID">44414</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67478)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 44414)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1370:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Walwyns jvst defence against the aspertions cast upon him in a late un-Christian pamphlet entituled Walwyns wiles / by William Walwyn.</title>
                  <author>Walwyn, William, 1600-1681.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. Hils for W. Larnar,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Walwyn, William, 1600-1681.</term>
               <term>Walwyns wiles.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Puritan Revolution, 1642-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:44414:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:44414:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>WALWYNS</hi> JVST DEFENCE AGAINST THE ASPERTIONS CAST UPON HIM, IN A late un-chriſtian Pamphlet entituled, <hi>WALWYNS WILES.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>William Walwyn,</hi> Merchant.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Proverbs 12. ver. 6.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>The words of the wicked are to lie in waite for blood, but the mouth of the upright ſhall deliver them.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>H. Hils,</hi> for <hi>W. Larnar,</hi> and are to be ſold at the ſign of the <hi>Blackmore,</hi> near <hi>Biſhops-gate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>M. DC. XLIX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:44414:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:44414:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Walwyns</hi> juſt defence againſt the Aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions caſt upon him, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> ſhould be glad for the good of humane ſociety, that thoſe ſeven men whoſe names are ſubſcribed to the Epiſtle of that Book, would ſet down a certain rule, or declare what rule theirs is, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by in civil Communication, a man may know, when thoſe he keeps company withall are reall; and when deceivers, when they mean as they ſeem, and when they carry two faces under one hood, which amongſt honeſt men is called double-dealing; and this not ſo much in reſpect of themſelves, for I have not had much familiarity with any of theſe ſeven; but in reſpect of thoſe from whom they ſeem to have had their falſe informations concerning me; there being not one of them that ever reproved me to my face for any thing I ever ſaid or did, or that ever applied themſelves to me with Friends in a Chriſtian way, to ſhew we wherein I walked erroniouſly or ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalouſly: but all they have done or ſpoken to my diſparagement, hath been behind my back; whil'ſt, whereſoever they met me, they nevertheleſſe ſaluted me as a Friend: How this kind of behaviour can be juſtified, I profeſſe I underſtand not.</p>
            <p>And upon what grounds theſe ſeven men ſubſcribe this Epiſtle, I do not appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend; for, as for Mr <hi>Kiffin,</hi> I never had an unfriendly word or countenance from him; nor from Mr <hi>Roſier,</hi> but kind reſpects wherever I met them: for Mr <hi>Foſter,</hi> and Mr <hi>Burnet,</hi> I know them not by name, not can't gheſſe who they are: Mr <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall,</hi> and Mr <hi>Price,</hi> have been ſomewhat ſhy a good while, about our different judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for ſeaſons of petitioning; but eſpecially, ſince at <hi>Kingſton,</hi> before his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, I gave my reaſons againſt the raiſing of a new Regiment for the Tower of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don;</hi> propoſing the place to be guarded with Citizens, as a means to preſerve trade, and the affection of the City to the Army; which I ſtill judge was honeſt and good councel: but their Friends purſued the contrary, and prevailed; and ever ſince, theſe have caſt an ill eie upon me, and as I have heard, have reproacht me much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind my back.</p>
            <p>And for Mr <hi>Arnald,</hi> juſt before the New Model, he groundleſly reported to the Lieutenant Generall <hi>Cromwel,</hi> that I held correſpondence with <hi>Oxford,</hi> though at the ſame time I held daily meetings, and intimate Diſcourſe with Mr <hi>John Goodwin,</hi> Mr <hi>Henry Burton,</hi> Mr <hi>Peters,</hi> Mr <hi>Hilſly,</hi> Mr <hi>Lilburn,</hi> and others, and continued ſo after with the beſt reſpect; but I could never get ſo much ſatisfaction among them for ſo groſſe an injury, as to know his Author, I only was anſwered, that I ſaw none of them had an ill thought of me: but ſince he underſtood I knew of this his injury to me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:44414:3"/> he hath ever hated me, and ſought to do me miſchief; giving out confidently, that I am a Jeſuite; and he now fixes his name, I fear, malliciouſly, to things I am ſure it is impoſſible for him to know or for any man in the world: for what is falſe hath no eſſence or reallity; but it is ſutable to his practiſe towards me, and ſo I wonder not to finde his name there: though at others, I cannot ſufficiently wonder:</p>
            <p>In the yeer 1646. whilſt the army was victorious abroad, through the union and concurrence of conſcientious people, of all judgments, and opinions in religion; there brake forth here about <hi>London</hi> a ſpirit of perſecution; whereby private meetings were moleſted, &amp; divers paſtors of congregations impriſoned, &amp; all threatned; Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> and others, fell foule upon them, with his Gangreen after Gangreen, ſlander upon ſlander, to make them odious, and ſo to fit them for deſtruction, whether by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of law, or open violence he ſeemed not to regard; and amongſt the reſt, abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed me, which drew from me <hi>a whiſper in his ear,</hi> and ſome other diſcourſes, tending ſo my own vindication, and the defence of all conſcientious people: and for which had then much reſpect from theſe very men, that now aſperſe me themſelves, with the very ſame, and ſome other like aſpertions, as he then did.</p>
            <p>Perſecution increaſed in all quarters of the land, ſad ſtories coming dayly from all parts, which at length were by divers of the Churches, my ſelf, and other friends, drawn into a large petition; which I profeſſe was ſo lamentable, conſidering the time, that I could hardly read it without tears: and though moſt of thoſe that are called Anabaptiſts and Browniſts congregations, were for the preſenting of it; yet Maſter <hi>Goodwins</hi> people, and ſome other of the Independent Churches being againſt the ſeaſon, it was never delivered.</p>
            <p>But troubles ſtill increaſing, another petition, not ſo large, was prepared, and at length agreed to by all ſorts of conſcientious people, that were oppoſite to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution: and all this while I was acceptable among them; only ſome grudgings I perceived in Maſter <hi>John Price,</hi> which I imputed to ſome <hi>weaknes, it clyning to emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> and all the ſtriſe about this petition alſo, was the ſeaſon: multitudes with me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the preſenting, and the Independents againſt it: in concluſion, a finall meeting there was, where before I came was diſperſt the moſt ſhamefull aſpertion of me, that ever was uttered of man: and which did render me ſo obnoxious to that meeting, that all I ſpake was conſtrued to the worſt; and cauſed ſo great a clamour and diſcontent, that he who had the petition and hands in keeping, rent it in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eeces; and ſo the meeting ended.</p>
            <p>Towards the concluſion whereof, Major <hi>Robert Cobet</hi> pulls me by the arm to ſpeak with me, ſo I took Maſter <hi>Davis,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Antrobus</hi> and others with me; and maſter <hi>Cobet</hi> told me before them, that one maſter <hi>Husbands</hi> a linnen draper in Corn hill, being at Lieutenant Generalls houſe, there openly avouched that I was an Athieſt and denier of Scriptures, a looſe and vitious man, and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>buſing my ſelf with a lew'd woman, ſhe puting me in mind of that place of Scripture, <hi>that whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers and adulterers God would judge,</hi> that I ſhould make anſwer, what do ye tell me of that Idle book?</p>
            <p>Telling me withall, that this report was gone all about the town, and was the cauſe I was ſo ill reſented by the preſent meeting; I confeſs, I was amazed to hear this, but whilſt he was telling me this foule ſtory, he eſpies maſter <hi>Hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bands,</hi> and calls him to us; telling him he was declaring to maſter <hi>Walwyn</hi> here, pointing to me, what he heard him declare at the Lieutenant Generalls, ſays maſter <hi>Husbands,</hi> I wiſh you had not ſpoken of it, for I find it is a miſtake, the thing is not true of maſter <hi>Walwyn,</hi> it is another; ſo he ſuffered himſelf to be thorowly reproved by thoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:44414:3"/> and he ſeemed then to be ſorry for it; but aſperſions fly faſter, then any man can fetch them back, and ſo did this, to my extream deſparagement: and it ſerved their turn at that meeting to blaſt all the reaſon I ſpake, and to deſtroy that peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</p>
            <p>And thoſe who had made uſe of this reproach, and ſo made themſelves guilty, as the manner of men is, reſolved to diſparage me to purpoſe, and thereupon ſome leading people of maſter <hi>John Goodwins,</hi> ſet themſelves down as a Committee, calling before them, all they could finde had ever converſed with me, to inform whatſoever I had ſaid, that might tend to my diſparagement: this is ſome three yeers ſince: and ſo by way of articles, moſt of the aſperſions now in this book, were then collected, which I had continuall notice of as they came in, and who did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form: and who would not, but declared confidently they were perſwaded from long and much familiarity, that I was really honeſt and conſcientious; amongſt which Mr. <hi>Henry Brandriff, Captain Chaplain,</hi> Mr. <hi>Weekes</hi> and others;</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſſe the violent party, as Mr. <hi>John Price,</hi> and others, would go on with their articles: me thoughts it was a ſtrange work, for a people who called themſelves the people of God: but ſo they did; and at length had poſſeſt divers, who formerly had well reſpected me, that I was a dangerous man and not fit for ſociety; whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it was deſired by my friends, and agreed unto by theirs, that a meeting ſhould be on both parties; and their articles ſhould be heard, and I have freedom to make my defence, and the place appointed was the <hi>Dolphin</hi> in <hi>Corn-hill,</hi> where I and my friends kept our time and continued there, but on their parts none came.</p>
            <p>And Mr. <hi>Brandriff,</hi> my then intimate friend, perſwaded me it was not fit, things ſhould come to ſuch a height, that it would make but rejoycing for our enemies; that he was confident, there was no real enmity, but only cauſles doubts and jealouſies, and that if I would but vindicate my judgement concerning the Scriptures, and my own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them, I ſhould find they had nothing to object againſt me, and that they and I ſhould be as good and as loving friends as ever.</p>
            <p>Whereunto I was very inclinable, as having never born any man a grudge for any injury ever done me, eſteeming the doer by wounding his own conſcience; to be puniſhed ſufficiently; nor do I relate theſe things in way of revenge, but only as to do my ſelf right, and to free my wife and children from the reproach of having ſo unworthy a huſband and Father; and the cauſe I honour, from having ſo vile a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant as theſe would make me, I told him my whiſper to Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> and my other writings did ſufficiently teſtifie I owned the Scriptures, and he confeſt it, but yet wiſht me to do ſomething particularly, to that end:</p>
            <p>About this time upon occaſion of Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> writings (I take it) came forth Mr. <hi>John Goodwins Haggi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>-Maſtix,</hi> wherein to the apprehenſion of ſome eminent men: he in effect denied the ſcriptures to be the word of God, and much diſcourſe, and great complaint there was about it, in ſo much as Collonel <hi>Leighs</hi> Committee had it brought before them, where it was my lot to be, when the paſſage concerning the Scriptures was read openly by one, thatamongſt others, informed againſt it: and where it was called a moſt impious, blaſphemous Book, and ordered to be ſeized, all of them immediatly;</p>
            <p>That Committee was of a moſt perſecuting diſpoſition, and dealt moſt forwardly with divers conſcientious people; with whom, and in whoſe behalf; I continually ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, as for Mr. <hi>Kiffin,</hi> Mr. <hi>Patience,</hi> and many others, I cannot now remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: and <hi>Henry,</hi> Mr. <hi>Overtons</hi> man the book-ſeller, that, as I am told, prints this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian book, called, <hi>Walwyns Wiles,</hi> might remember who it was that gave timely
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:44414:4"/> notice of the order for ſeizing his Maſter's Books (for he pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted <hi>Hagio Maſtix)</hi> and in thanfulneſſe for the courteſie done to his dead Maſter, might have forborn to have done me ſuch a diſcourteſie: but it hath been my uſuall payment for all my ſervices to that ſort of men.</p>
            <p>Divers did obſerve a ſtrange providence, that thoſe who had ſo ſcandalized me for a denier of Scriptures, ſhould from a pen, wherein they were all concerned, receive occaſion of ſo great ſuſpicion, and be put themſelves upon a work of vindication on his behalf: And though they called it, <hi>a Candle to light the Sun</hi> (as eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming it altogether ſuperfluous) yet many ſtill ſay, it needs to be more clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            <p>And hence ſome of my Friends perſwaded me I needed not to publiſh my Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation concerning the Scriptures, for ſatisfaction of thoſe, who had enough to do for their own Vindication: yet becauſe I was willing to ſtand clear in the ſight of all men, I publiſhed my <hi>Still and foft voyce,</hi> againſt which I never yet heard any obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: And one of Mr <hi>Goodwin's</hi> People, namely, Mr <hi>Daveniſh,</hi> meeting me a few daies after in the Court of Requeſts, ſaluted me kindly, and gave me thanks for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing that Book; I told him, I was glad underſtanding men approved it, and did hope it would be profitable to the publique: he replyed, it would be ſo, and that he ſhould make it his rule.</p>
            <p>And ſo a good while after this, I had much reſpect from many o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them, and not an ill look from any: but though Mr <hi>Leigh's</hi> Committee extremely perplexed ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt people about their private meetings and doctrines, yet did this ſort of men that traduce me appear very ſlenderly in compariſon of others, that were thought to be leſſe concerned.</p>
            <p>In concluſion, that Committee and their Favourers in both Houſes grew to ſo great a height, that the Generality of Congregations, and others, reſolved to bear teſtimony openly againſt the ſame, as being contrary to the many Declarations of Parliament, and as doing the very ſame things they had condemned in the high Commiſſion: and thereupon drew up a Petition, wherein they did parallel all the former practiſes complained of in the Star Chamber and high Commiſſion, with the preſent proceedings; which Petition was drawn and debated by many perſons cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen purpoſely thereunto, and indeed was the moſt ſerious of any that was preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted (which the Author of this Pamphlet, I perceive, tearms ſharp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſe and provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king) and imputes it unto me.</p>
            <p>This Petition was taken before it was handed, and queſtioned as a ſcandalous and ſeditious paper, and committed to Mr <hi>Leigh's</hi> Committee to enquire after the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors and Promoters; and Mr <hi>Lamb,</hi> at whoſe meeting place it was taken, ordered to appear there: this occaſioned a very great appearance in the owning of it, by aboundance of conſciencious honeſt people, and that occaſioned ſome diſcontent in the Committee, which begot the commitment of Major <hi>Tulidah,</hi> and Mr <hi>Tue;</hi> and that occaſioned another Petition to the Houſe, and that another, un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill the laſt and the firſt large one were ordered to be burnt by the common Hangma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; in all which time of motion and trouble, moſt of the uppermoſt Independents ſtood a loof, and look'd on: whil'ſt Mr <hi>Staſmore,</hi> Mr <hi>Highland,</hi> Mr <hi>Davis,</hi> Mr <hi>Cooper,</hi> Mr <hi>Thomas Lamb</hi> of the Spittle, and very many more, for many weeks continually plied the Houſe.</p>
            <p>The Petition is yet to be ſeen, and is fraught with aboundance of good things, ſuch as I really deſired the Houſe would have granted; and I think it had been hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py for them that burnt it, rather to have granted it, and moſt happy for the Common-wealth;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:44414:4"/> So that it's an extreme miſtake to imagine, that I, or any that I ever knew, petitioned for ſuch things as we did hope the Parliament would not grant: Indeed, we had cauſe to doubt they would not, but we conceived they ought, the things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing evidently juſt; and we conceived if they would not, 'twas more then we knew before we aſk'd; and we knew it was our duty to aſk, and that upon ſuch evidence of reaſon and equity which that Petition holds forth, as ſhould leave a teſtimony to the world, that we underſtood our rights, and did in an humble petitioning way demand them.</p>
            <p>But this buſtling unkind dealing with Petitioners for many weeks together, and the burning of a Petition ſo juſt and neceſſary, ſo opened the eies of the people in all places, that it was both grieved and wondred at; all men evidently ſeeing, that we were likely, though the <hi>Common Enemy</hi> was vanquiſh'd, to be liable to the ſame, or worſe bondage, notwithſtanding all the bloud and miſery it had coſt to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered there from.</p>
            <p>And when this was diſcerned, then ſome of my now Adverſaries began to approve of our motions, and they and I began to come a little nearer together, and had joynt meetings and debates; and Mr <hi>John Price</hi> may, and cannot but remember an eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings journey he and I made into <hi>Drury</hi>-lane to the Lieutenant Generall, and what ſatisfaction we received; what aboundance of friendly diſcourſe we had all the way going and comming, and parted in a moſt kind and cordiall manner; rejoycing on my part, as having no grain of rancour remaining in me, and thought it had been ſo on his; if it were not, God forgive him.</p>
            <p>But the effect was, we all, both his Friends and mine, joyned in a Petition, the laſt and moſt ſharp of any, as is yet to be ſeen; wherein he knows was not only his and mine advice, but many others: ſo that to ſay, I delight or deſign provocations to Authority, is a groſſe abuſe; if there were any, it is, he knows, to be ſhared amongſt he knows whom, as well as us.</p>
            <p>And, as unadviſed, it is to lay to my charge the oppoſing of all Authority that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was: for let them tell me what Authority they oppoſed not; the Kings and Biſhops they cannot deny; and the Parliament and Preſbyterian, I think, they will confeſſe; and truly I never oppoſed ſince, except to inſiſt for ſuch juſt things as were promiſed, when the Army firſt diſputed, be called an oppoſition: and ſuch as are not only fix'd in my mind, but in the minds of thouſands more that then ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the proceedings of the Army, and ventered their lives for them, when theſe that now revile me, ſtood aloof, ſeeing it neither juſt nor ſeaſonable.</p>
            <p>And truly, that they have ſate themſelves down on this ſide <hi>Iordan,</hi> the reaſon is ſomewhat too evident, for men that would not be thought men of this world; it is but a promiſed land, a promiſed good that I and my Friends ſeek, it is neither offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, honours nor preferments, it is only promiſed Freedom, and exemption from burdens for the whole Nation, not only for our ſelves; we wiſh them peace, we repine not at any mans honour, preferment or advantage; give us but Common Right, ſome foundations, ſome boundaries, ſome certainty of Law, and a good Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; that now, when there is ſo high diſcourſe of Freedom, we may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from will, power, and meer arbitrary diſcretion, and we ſhall be ſatisfied: if to inſiſt for this, be to oppoſe Authority, what a caſe are we in? Certainly were theſe men in our caſe, or were they ſenſible of the price it hath coſt this Nation to purchaſe Freedom, they would think it deſerved more then the meer name there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:44414:5"/>
            <p>And how I can be charged to make it my work to divide the Army, I cannot ſee; I only purſue the eſtabliſhment of Freedom, and redreſſe of Grievances, I have ever purſued, and which are not yet obtained; ſo alſo have done many in the Army. It is in the Army, as it is between theſe mens Friends and mine; ſome content themſelves with preſent enjoyments, others with the Commonwealth at more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty in the foundations of Freedom; and for my part, I ever moſt earneſtly deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their union, ſo it were in good, and for that Freedom and good to the Nation, for which, I believe, moſt of them have fought; and if they divide for want of it, they divide them that keep them from it, and not I, that wiſh with all my heart that cauſe of diviſion were not.</p>
            <p>The Lieutenant Generall well knows (for I viſited him often in <hi>Drury</hi>-lane about that time that Mr <hi>Price</hi> was there with me) how much I deſired the union of the Army; and though it then divided, it was not eſteemed a fault in thoſe that ſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelves for good, but blame worthy in thoſe that would not unite, except for evil: So that to unite, or divide, is not the thing; but whether in good, or evil, is the main of all; and by which, my Adverſaries and I ſhall one day be judged, though now they have taken the Chair, and moſt uncharitably judge me of evil in every thing wherein I move, or but open my mouth.</p>
            <p>And the Lieutenant Generall alſo knows, upon what grounds I then perſwaded him to divide from that Body, to which he was united; that if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e did not, it would be his ruine, and the ruine of the Generall, and of all thoſe Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thyes that had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved us; that if he did do it in time, he ſhould not only preſerve himſelf and them, and all conſciencious people, but he ſhould do it without ſpilling one drop of bloud; profeſſing, that if it were not evident to me that it would be ſo, I would not perſwade him; and that I would undertake to demonſtrate to him that it would be ſo; and ſo, through God's goodneſſe, and the zeal and affections of theſe mens now deſpiſed Friends, it came to paſſe: ſo far was I ever from: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>viſing unto bloud: whereas theſe men would ſuppoſe me to be delighted with nothing more then ſlaughter and confuſion.</p>
            <p>Well, I had no ſhew of enmity from them all the time the Army diſputed with the Parliament, but they would, divers of them, come home to my houſe day by day, and ſit and diſcourſe friendly, and chearfully, and ſeriouſly, of the preſent af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, and refreſh themſelves in my Garden with that ſimple entertainment I uſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my Friends; and when they had done, I would bring them on their way, and they as kindly bring me back; and ſo joy'd was I really with this (as I thought) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed affection, that I would often ſay within my ſelf, and to ſome others, I now ſee, <hi>The falling out of Lovers is the renewing of Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, ſo great a teſtimony I then had, from my continued Fr end Mr <hi>Brandriffe,</hi> that greater could not be; for it was his lot to diſcourſe with one Major <hi>Weſt,</hi> a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, I take it, of <hi>Cambridge-ſhire,</hi> who was to have gone for <hi>Ireland:</hi> this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man told him divers ſecret things, that rightly ordered, were very uſefull at that time: Mr <hi>Brandriffe</hi> thinks me the fitteſt man to be acquainted therewith, tels me of it, and brings him to my houſe, to whom I was not altogether a S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ranger; ſo he opens his breaſt to me in ſuch things, that as the times were, if I had been baſe, or falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted, might have coſt him his life; I ſay, as the times were: but I proved as Mr <hi>Brandriffe</hi> had reported me to him, and kept his councel.</p>
            <p>Well, very good Friends we were all; and I was by very eminent perſons of the Army, ſent for to <hi>Reading,</hi> to be adviſed withall touching the good of the people, a ſtudy my Conſcience had much addicted me to; and after this, no jarr appeared
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:44414:5"/> amongſt us till the Army had paſt through the City, nor untill the buſineſſe of the Tower afore-mentioned beſell: But then, inſtead of Arguments againſt mine, and my Friends Reaſon, aſperſions were produced; and then afreſh, we were Atheiſts, Non-Scripturiſts, Jeſuites, and any thing to render us odious. This, whil'ſt I remained there, begot a great falling out amongſt our Friends and theirs in <hi>London;</hi> which upon my comming (looking upon it as a thing of very ill conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence) I prevailed for a reconcilement: ſo far have I ever been from dividing, that I believe all thoſe with whom I have moſt converſt, judge no man more deſerves the name of a Reconciler.</p>
            <p>But about this time I met with that Gentleman, Major <hi>Weſt,</hi> in the ſtreet, and he looks upon me ſomewhat ghaſtly, ſaying, what are you here? yes, ſaid I, why not? why, ſaies he, being at my Lord Mayors, you were there ſaid to be the moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, ill-conditioned man alive; that you ſeek to have the City deſtroyed; that you would have no Government, and all things common, and drive on dangerous deſigns: ſaies I, who is it that avouches this? why, ſaies he, <hi>Henry Brandriffe,</hi> who ſaies, he knows it to be true, and that he hath kept you company theſe ſeven years, of purpoſe to diſcover you: I profeſſe, I was ſo aſtoniſht to hear this from Mr <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>driffe,</hi> that I had no thought (nor did not then call to mind) how upon intimate intire friendſhip, he had brought this Mr <hi>Weſt</hi> to unboſome himſelf unto me, in a matter of ſo great concernment; ſo I paſt it over, and parted with him.</p>
            <p>But in a little ruminating of the ſtrangeneſſe and horribleneſſe of this dealing, the buſineſſe of Major <hi>Weſts</hi> comming to me with Mr <hi>Brandriffe,</hi> withall circumſtances came freſh into my mind; and about a week after, I met with Major <hi>Weſt</hi> in <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi>-gate-ſtreet, and after a ſalute, aſkt him, if he had ſeen Mr <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>driffe:</hi> he told me, he had, and that he was of the ſame mind, and would juſtifie it, for he had kept me company ſeven years to diſcover me: upon this I aſkt him, whether he did not remember, that Mr <hi>Brandriffe</hi> (upon pre-diſcourſe) did bring him to my houſe to diſcover ſuch and ſuch things to me, as the fitteſt Friend he had? he anſwered me, yes: and were they not ſuch things, ſaid I, that if I had been baſe and deceitfull, might have been much to your prejudice, as the times then were? yes, ſaies he: ſaid I, did he then know me to be baſe, and to carry on dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous deſigns, and had kept me company ſeven years to diſcover me, and would he bring you to diſcover ſuch things, and to un boſome your ſelf to me? ſaid I, whether was he moſt falſe to you, or to me? he makes a ſtand a little while; truly, ſaies he, he muſt be very falſe and unworthy to one of us: So I wiſht him to conſider, what ſtrange kind of men theſe were, and how a man might come to know when they meant good faith in their diſcourſe and ſociety amongſt men.</p>
            <p>This Diſcourſe I have ſet down thus punctually, becauſe a perſon of ſo good cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit as this Major <hi>Weſt</hi> is, is ready, as he told me lately, to avouch this that Mr <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>driffe</hi> ſaid of me; and becauſe it is their uſuall way to beget credit in the fouleſt aſperſions they caſt upon me, by ſaying, this is certain, I kept him company ſo long of purpoſe to diſcover him, and will rather injure their own conſcience then want of belief; for I am confident Mr <hi>Brandriffe</hi> in all his ſociety with me, had not an ill thought of me; if he did keep me company ſo long for ill and unworthy ends, to entrap and make the worſt of every thing I ſaid (which I cannot believe) he was the more unworthy; and cannot but lament his condition, or any mans elſe that uſeth it: I bleſſe God, I never was a minute in his company, but upon tearms of true hearty love and friendſhip; nor ever circumvented him, or any man elſe; nor have uſed to carry tales, or to make the worſt of men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> diſcourſes, but have ſet my houſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:44414:6"/> and heart open at all times to honeſt men, where they have had a moſt ſincere and hearty welcome; and if any have turned my freedom and kindneſſe to my preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, God forgive them.</p>
            <p>Yea, ſo far hath it been from being my principle, or practice as the uncharitable Subſcribers of the Epiſtle Dedicatory to this-vain Book, infer) to ſay or do any thing againſt him whom I thought engaged to deſtroy me; that both to thoſe of the Kings Party, with whom I had ſome acquaintance, and thoſe my old and many Friends of the Preſbyterian judgment, in all times; I ever ſpake and adviſed them what I thought in my conſcience was for their good; perſwading with all men to place their happineſſe ſo, as it might be conſiſtent with the freedom, peace and proſperity of the Commonwealth; and, I believe, many will acknowledge they have found my councel good, and wiſh they had taken it; ſome having ſince confeſt, I have told them truth, when they did not believe it; nor can any of them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſtly ſay, and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve will not ſay, that ever I abated one ſillable of my principle of Common Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, nor ever diſcovered a thought to the prejudice of the Parliament or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</p>
            <p>But would theſe men turn their ſight inward, and look into their own hearts, there they would find ſuch a latitude of diſſimulation, as is hardly to be found in any ſort of men pretending to Religion; as may not only appear by theſe mens fair car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages outwardly alwaies to me, and Mr <hi>Brandriffe</hi>'s ſtrange diſcovery of himſelf, but in others alſo of the ſame people, as Mr <hi>Richard Price</hi> the Scrivener, the Author of one of the moſt notorious falſe ſcandals contained in the Book.</p>
            <p>My firſt acquaintance with this Mr <hi>Richard Price,</hi> was by occa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion of our Pariſh buſineſſe, in his trade, and that about our Ward; and after that, about a Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance preſented to the Common Councel, in all which I found him ingenuous, and ſo grew to intimacy with him: this was when Alderman <hi>Pennington</hi> was Lord Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yor, and before Mr <hi>John Goodwin</hi> had gathered his Church, or at leaſt, before this Mr <hi>Price</hi> was a Member of it; and I took ſo much content in his company, that I brought ſuch as I loved moſt entirely, acquainted with him.</p>
            <p>I, through God's goodneſſe, had long before been eſtabliſhed in that part of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine (called then, Antinomian) of free juſtification by Chriſt alone; and ſo my heart was at much more eaſe and freedom, then others, who were entangled with thoſe yokes of bondage, unto which Sermons and Doctrines mixt of Law and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, do ſubject diſtreſſed conſciences: upon which point, I was frequent in diſcourſe with him, and he would frequently come home to my houſe, and took much delight in that company he found there; inſomuch, as we fell to practice arms in my-Garden: and whither he brought his Friends; and Lords daies, and Faſt daies he ſpen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> uſually with us: As for Faſts then, ſome circumſtances of the times and proceedings conſidered, neither he nor we were ſatisfied therein, nor hardly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of thoſe that we called Sectaries (or Antinomians, which was then the beam in the e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e) about the Town.</p>
            <p>It ſell out upon a Faſt day in the morning, my Friend and I thought fit to give, him a viſit, to manifeſt our joy in his ſociety: ſo comming to his houſe, he ſeemed to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eding glad, and haſtned abroad with us, and we went at laſt to <hi>Baſing-ſhaw</hi> Church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eing where my Lord Mayor was to be, as expecting to hear ſome excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent man there; being there ſome time, we found the matter ſo lamentable, as we were all three weary of it: For the truth is, whoſoever is clearly poſſeſt with this one Doctrine of <hi>Free Juſtification,</hi> hath ſuch a touchſtone as preſently diſcovers the leaſt contradiction either in Praiers, or Sermons, and what is gold, ſilver, droſſe,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:44414:6"/> hay or ſtubble: ſo we all at once together went away, but ſo, as we could give no offence to the congregation, being not in the body of the Church; (ſo that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, in ſaying we had been from Church to Church) Mr. <hi>Cranfords</hi> being all we were at before, though he know, it hath not been more uſuall with-any then with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, paſſing to and fro from place to place on the Lords, and Faſts dayes, 4 and 6 of a company ſpying, watching, and cenſuring of doctrines (as he that wrote the Book called the <hi>Pullpit incendiary,</hi> me thinks ſhould be aſham'd to ſeeme ignorant of.</p>
            <p>Being come out of the Church, we paſt the way home-wards; much lamenting the condition of a people under ſuch teachers, being taught ſcarce any thing to make them either knowing Chriſtians, or good and uſefull men; imputing much of the miſery of the times to the ignorance or preverſneſſe of preachers; the greateſt part of their time being ſpent to uphold their intereſt againſt <hi>Antinomians, Anabaptiſts,</hi> and others, that fell off from their congregations, ſeldom upon any neceſſary or uſefull doctrine, or if they did, before they had done with it, they contradicted themſelves much or little, ſufficient to ſpoil all they had done.</p>
            <p>So in ſhort time, we came to my houſe, where we went on diſcourſing, from one thing to another, and amongſt other things, of the wiſdom of the heathen, how wiſe and able they were in thoſe things, unto which their knowledge did extend; and what pains they took to make men wiſe, vertuous, and good common-wealths men; how pertinent they were in the things they undertook, to the ſahme of ſuch Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, as took upon them to be teachers of others, when they were to ſeeke in the main principle of their ſcience, with which kinde of diſcourſe, he was very much affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, though it did not appear he had been accuſtomed to the reading of humane au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors; which for twenty yeers before I had been, but I uſed them alwayes in their due place; being very ſtudious all that time in the Scriptures, and other divine au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, as ſome of Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> works, Mr. <hi>Downhams</hi> divinity, I had, as it were, without book, alſo Doctor <hi>Halls</hi> meditations, and vowes, and his heaven upon earth, and thoſe peeces annexed to Mr. <hi>Hookers Eccleſiaſtical pollicy;</hi> hearing, and reading continually; uſing <hi>Seneca, Plutarchs Lives,</hi> and <hi>Charon of humane wiſdom,</hi> as things of recreation, wherein I was both pleaſed, and profited; and truly, I do not ſee I have cauſe to repent me of taking liberty in this kinde, having never in my life, I bleſſe God; made an ill uſe thereof, amongſt which <hi>Lucian</hi> for his good ends, in diſovering the vanity of things in worldly eſteem, I like very well, whereof I can read only ſuch as are tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh;</hi> ſuch a wiſe Jeſuite I am, that withall my ſkill, I cannot conſtrue three lines of any <hi>Latin</hi> author, nor do underſtand any, except ſuch common proverbs, as are more familiar in <hi>Latine</hi> then in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> which ſometimes I uſe not to dignifie my ſelfe, but becauſe of the pertinency of them in ſome occaſions.</p>
            <p>For as this author would infer of me, I do not think any man much the wiſer for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving many languages, or for having more then one; &amp; though I wiſh I had the <hi>Latin,</hi> yet I think it not worth that paines, and time, as is commonly ſpent in learning; and do beleeve, I had been furniſht with it, (for my parents, I thank them, were not wanting) but for the tediouſneſſe, and impertinency of my teachers; which ſince I underſtand, I often blame in them, which is all I have to ſay againſt <hi>Latin,</hi> or any kind of learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; except that part of it, which puffeth up, and makes men ſcornfull pedants, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſers of unlearned and illitterate men, a humour, if I miſtake not puffeth my preſent Antagoniſt:</p>
            <p>I ſee wiſe, and inconſiderate men too, ſkillfull in languages, and in arts, and ſcience; I have not much to do with them; my care is rightly to underſtand my ſelf in my native language, being troubled with no other; and of all I chiefly thank theſe that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:44414:7"/> employ there charity in tranſlation of well meaning authors, which I hope I may read without aſking leave of theſe that through ſcupuloſity dare not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> was ſkilfull in all the learning of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> which the Scriptures teſtifie without reproof, and S. <hi>Paul</hi> certainly read the poets, and was not abaſht to recite one of them; and I am certain moſt of the univerſity men in England, and moſt of the liberaries are not without all <hi>Lucians</hi> works, ſome whereof, as I am informed, are much more offencive to Chriſtianity then theſe in <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And why then I might not without blemiſh read one of his dialogues to this, Mr. <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Price,</hi> I cannot yet perceive? as I take it we read that which is called his tyrant; a diſcourſe, though poſſibly not in all things juſtifiable, yet ſuch as he might have made a better uſe of, being ſo pointed againſt ambition, pride and coveteouſneſſe as he might have been the better for it whilſt he lived: as for me I count him a very weak man, that takes harm by reading it or any ſuch like things.</p>
            <p>The truth is, for many yeers my books, and teachers were maſters in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of me; I durſt ſcarce undertake to judge of the things I either Read, or heard: but having digeſted that <hi>unum neceſſarium,</hi> that pearle in the field, free juſtification by Chriſt alone; I became maſter of what I heard, or read, in divin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty: and this doctrine working by love; I became alſo, much more maſter of my affections, and of what ever I read in humane authors, which I ſpeak nor as Glorying in my ſelf, but in the author of that bleſſed principle; which I did long before, and then (and do ſtill) prize at ſo ineſtimable a value; that I was far from any ſuch thought of impious blaſphemy, as to ſay, here is more wit in this (meaning <hi>Lucian)</hi> then in all the bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le: all our diſcourſe was before my wiſe and children, and my friend, and a maid ſervant that had dwelt with us then three yeers, and ſince hath made them up nine yeers; <hi>I</hi> dare appeale to them all if ever they heard me value, any, or all the Books, or Sermons either, in the world Comparable to the Bible; ſo as, but that <hi>I</hi> have ſince had ſome experience of the eaſineſſe of Mr. <hi>Price</hi> his conſcience? <hi>I</hi> ſhould even expire with wonder, at his impudence, and at his uncharitableneſſe, that he and his friends, people of a Church, that call themſelves Saints, and a people of God, ſhould harbour this wretched ſlander ſix yeares amongſt them, and be bringing it forth this time, and that time, but finde no time, their ſeaſon, but when I was violently taken out of my bed, and houſe, and made a priſoner: if this be their way of viſiting of priſoners, would not it make men think they had forgot the Scriptures; nay, might they not go to the heathens to learn ſome Charity.</p>
            <p>Where is Charity? Where is love? that true Chriſtian love, which covereth a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of ſins; but that there ſhould be malice, inventive, inveterate malice, in place thereof: certainly were your Church truly a Church of Chriſts making, it would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a heavy Cenſure.</p>
            <p>Our Saviour ſends the ſluggard to the Ant: the over carefull and diſtruſtfull to the lilies of the field, and may not I ſend theſe to heathens, to get ſome charity?</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Price,</hi> I bluſh not to ſay, I have been long accuſtomed to read <hi>Montaigns Eſſaies,</hi> an author perhaps youle ſtartle at; nor do I approve of him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n all things, but ile read you a peece or two, that will be worth your ſtudy; though he be an author ſcarce ſo modeſt as our <hi>Lucian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Speaking in his 12 chap. pag. 244. of Chriſtian religion, he ſaith thus,</p>
            <p>
               <q>If this ray of Divinity, did in any ſort touch us, it would every where appear: not only our words, but our actions, would bear ſome ſhew, &amp; luſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of it. Whatſoever ſhould proceed from us, might be ſeen inlightned, with this noble and matchleſſe brightneſſe. We ſhould bluſh for ſhame that in humane ſects, here was never any
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:44414:7"/> ſo factious, what difficulty or ſtrangeneſſe ſoever his Doctrine maintained; but would in ſome ſort conform his behaviour, and ſquare his life unto it; whereas ſo divine and heavenly an inſtitution, never marks Chriſtians but by the tongue: And will you ſee whether it be ſo? Compare but our manners unto a Turk, or a Pagan, and we muſt needs yeild unto them: whereas in reſpect of our religious ſuperiority, we ought by much, yea, by an incomparable diſtance out-ſhine them in excellency, And well might a man ſay. <hi>Are they ſo juſt, ſo charitable, and ſo good, then muſt they be Chriſtians.</hi> All other outward ſhows, and exteriour appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, are common to all Religions, as hope, affiance, events, ceremonies, peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, and Martyrdom; the peculiar badg of our truth ſhould be, virtue, as it is the heavenlyeſt, and moſt difficult mark, and worthyeſt production of verity it ſelf: And in his twentieth Chapter, pag: 102. he ſaies, ſpeaking of the <hi>Cannibals,</hi> the very words that import lying, falſhood, treaſon, diſſimulation, covetouſneſſe, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, detraction, and pardon, were never heard of amongſt them.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe, and the like flowers, I think it lawfull to gather out of his Wilderneſſe, and to give them room in my Garden; yet this worthy <hi>Montaign</hi> was but a Romiſh Catholique: yet to obſerve with what contentment and full ſwoln joy he recites theſe cogitations, is wonderfull to conſideration: And what now ſhall I ſay? Go to this honeſt Papiſt, or to theſe innocent <hi>Cannibals,</hi> ye Independent Churches, to learn civility, humanity, ſimplicity of heart; yea, charity and Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>This hath been an old long rooted ſlander, and hath therfore coſt me thus much labour to ſtock it up: As for my breach of the Faſt, one would think Mr <hi>John Goodwin</hi>'s playing at Bowls upon a Faſt day in the afternoon, a while after this, and which he did not ſeem to judge a fault, but as it was an offence againſt the reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his faculty, might have ſtopt theſe mens mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ths in that particular: Nor would I ever have revived the memory of it, but their triumphing thus in ſlanders againſt me, deſerves their abaſement and humiliation.</p>
            <p>Of whom this Mr <hi>Richard Price</hi> receives inſtruction, I know not; but this is he that with knowledge, if not direction of their Church, undertook to betray the KING into the hands of the Governour of <hi>Alisbury,</hi> under pretence of giving up <hi>Alisbury</hi> unto him, in lieu of Liberty of Conſcience (that was the gold upon the bait) and did go, and ſpake with him; and how many untruths in ſuch a caſe he forc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to utter with confidence, may eaſily be judg'd; and where he had a rule for this being a Chriſtian, for my part I am to ſeek; the Apoſtle thought himſelf inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that it was reported, he maintained that evil might be done, that good might come thereof.</p>
            <p>And ſince treachery ſeems ſo ſlight a matter, with theſe Church-men, I ſhall make bold to ſend them again to this Lord <hi>Mantaign,</hi> in his third Book, and firſt Chapter, pag: 443. he ſaith thus;</p>
            <p>
               <q>To whom ſhould not treachery be deteſtable, when <hi>Tiberius</hi> refuſed it on ſuch great intereſt? One ſent him word out of <hi>Germany,</hi> that if he thought good, <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minius</hi> ſhould be made away by poyſon; he was the mightyeſt enemy the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans had, who had ſo vilely uſed them under <hi>Varus,</hi> and who only impeached the increaſe of his Dominion in that Country; his anſwer was, That the People of <hi>Rome</hi> were accuſtomed to be revenged on their enemies by open courſes, with weapons in hand, not by ſubtilties, nor in hugger-mugger: thus left he the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for the honeſt, in 447. As for my part (ſaith <hi>Montaign)</hi> both my word and my faith are as the reſt, pieces of this common body, their beſt effect is the publique ſervice; that's ever pre-ſuppoſed with me: But as if one ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:44414:8"/> me to take charge of the Rols or Records of the Pallace, I would anſwer, I have no ſkill in them, or to be a Leader of Pioners; I would ſay, I am called to a worthier office: Even ſo, who would go about to employ me not to murther, or poyſon? but to lye, betray, or forſwear my ſelf, I would tell him, if I have rob'd or ſtoln any thing from any man, ſend me rather to the <hi>Galleys;</hi> for a Gentleman may lawfully ſpeak, as did the <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> defeated by <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ripater,</hi> upon the points of their Agreement; <hi>You may impoſe as heavy burthens, and harmfull taxes upon us, as you pleaſe; but you loſe your time to command us any ſhamefull or diſhoneſt thing.</hi> Every man ſhould give himſelf the oath which the Egypt an Kings ſolemnly and uſually preſented to their Judges, <hi>Not to ſwerve from their Conſciences,</hi> what command ſoever they ſhould receive from themſelves to the contrary.. In 448. he ſaith thus, What is leſſe poſſible for him to do, then what he cannot effect with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out charge unto his faith.</q>
            </p>
            <p>It will, <hi>I</hi> know, be wondred at, that <hi>I</hi> thus enlarge my ſelf; but theſe things are ſo rich and excellent, that <hi>I</hi> cannot but inſiſt upon them, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in ſome hope to convert my Adverſaries, which hath ever been my aim, equall to my own vindicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for <hi>I</hi> recite theſe paſſages, becauſe <hi>I</hi> am in love with them, wiſhing them alſo of the ſame mind, for <hi>I</hi> wiſh them no worſe then <hi>I</hi> wiſh to my ſelf: or if <hi>I</hi> fail of thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, yet <hi>I</hi> am deſirous and hopefull to better other men by the things <hi>I</hi> write.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the plainneſſes wherein <hi>I</hi> have ever delighted; ſo far; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m <hi>I</hi> from that po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique, crafty, ſubtil and hidden reſervedneſſe, which this Author would perſwade the world <hi>I</hi> abound withall; exerciſing his wit ſo exquiſitly in decyphering me out to be a man of ſo large capacity and ability, as for my part <hi>I</hi> do not believe there is any man in the world ſo; much leſſe my ſelf, who ſetting aſide a little conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and experience, united to an upright conſcience, have nothing to pleaſe my ſelf withall: Nor do <hi>I</hi> much deſire thoſe extraordinary parts, which are ſeldom em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to their right end, being commonly tempted, to ſerve ſome Politicians ends, as may be ſeen rather in the abilities and application of them, in this Author; for he hath drawn ſuch a picture of mans ability, as ſhews only his own parts in ſo doing; and applyes them to me, that have no part of them, of purpoſe to make me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> lifts me up to the top of the pinacle, that he may caſt me down to my greater <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Truly, <hi>I</hi> never thought a good cauſe ever needed ſuch workings is he exalts him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf (not me) withall: and <hi>I</hi> dare appeal to thoſe many my Friends, that <hi>I</hi> daily and hourly converſt withall for ſome years now in publique buſineſſes, whether ever they ſaw more plaineſſe and open-heartedneſſe in man: Indeed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f <hi>I</hi> ſuſpected any man inclinable to enſnare me, as theſe mens practiſes, made me of late ſomewhat wary; <hi>I</hi> had reaſon to be carefull. And whereas he taxes me of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eightening mens diſcontents, I believe till now, they are pleaſed (not without particular morſels) none were more apt thereto then themſelves: but the world is well am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nded with them, and every other mans mouth muſt be ſtopt on pain of Treaſon.</p>
            <p>I am not more pleaſed with the former ſayings of <hi>Montaign,</hi> then with what he ſaies in pag: 449.</p>
            <p>
               <q>I have the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rfore placed <hi>Epaminondas</hi> in the firſt rank of virtuous men, and now recant it not: unto what a high pitch raiſed he the conſideration of his particular duty? Who never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ew man he had vanquiſhed; Who for their valuable good of reſtoring his Country her liberty, made it a matter of Conſcience to take away any mans life, without a due and formall courſe of Law; and who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udged him a bad man (how good a Citizen ſoever) that amongſt his enemies, and in the ſury of a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:44414:8"/> battail, ſpared not his friend, or his hon, ſo here a mind of a rich compoſition.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And truly, I boaſt not, but theſe things have long ſince made ſo deep impreſsion in me, that I have been extreamly miſtaken by thoſe, that gave our, there was a plot amongſt us to murther the King, when he was at <hi>Hampton Court,</hi> and as much theſe that now ſtart, that other as baſe, of an intention to murther the Lieutenant Generall, they are wayes neither juſtifiable nor profitable; for where ſhould ſuch courſes end, or what could more diſparage that ſide that began it; <hi>I</hi> wiſh you would be but as carefull to preſerve intirely, the due and formall courſe of Law to every man, without exception, friend, or foe, as we have been: and though at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent you may pleaſe, your ſelves with the ſufferings of your adverſaries (as you fancy them) yet you do therein, but tread down your own hedges, and pluck up that Bank, that lets in the ſea of will, and power, over whelming your own liberties.</p>
            <p>But before <hi>I</hi> part with this Mr. <hi>Richard Price;</hi> I have another thing to lay to his charge, and that is; That he ſhould ſay, <hi>I</hi> had a hand in that plot where <hi>Read,</hi> and Sir <hi>Baſil-brook</hi> were in queſtion: in ſo much as my friends came running to me with tears in their eyes, and all from his unadviſed ſpeeches: was this like a friend, vvith vvhom you had eaten, and drunk, and diſcourſed familiarly, and from vvhom you had taken ſome ſmall tokens of ſincere affection; as the books entituled <hi>Luthers Chriſtian liberty, The benefits of Chriſts death, Freemans meditations, and is I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; Chriſts Councell to Loadicea,</hi> and <hi>ſince</hi> I vvas ſo far from retorting this injury upon you, as that after it, I choſe rather to convince you by love, and as a teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of my good reſpects to you, ſent you the <hi>Hyſtory of Thucidides,</hi> vvherevvith I vvas much delighted, truly I vvonder nothing could keep you from bearing me rancour thus long, and to vvatch this time of any, to ſlay me vvith your unjuſt report.</p>
            <p>And truly, upon occaſion lately, making my moan of this kinde of uſage to one of their ovvn people, that had received, extream prejudce againſt me upon theſe, &amp; the like falſe reports, vvhich upon ſome diſcourſe vvith a friend of mine firſt, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvards vvith my friend, and I together, he did profeſſe much greef, for my hard u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage; and told me that he did impute moſt of all this to pride, and emulation, from this Mr. <hi>Price,</hi> and in that my pen in Petitions (vvhich othervviſe vvas his vvork and trade) vvas many times accepted, if it be ſo it is a ſad ſtory indeed, his ovvn conſcience only knovvs vvhether it be ſo or not.</p>
            <p>Yet I cannot but fear moſt of all the injuryes of this nature <hi>I</hi> have received, have proceeded from this ground, for othervviſe I am certain, I have given no occaſion to that Congregation, vvhereas moſt of my reproaches come fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them. And ſince I am thus fallen upon Mr. <hi>Richard Price,</hi> there is yet another of that name of this congregation, and is this Mr. <hi>Richard Price</hi> his vnckle, and Mr. <hi>Hilleſlyes</hi> ſon in lavv: from this Mr. <hi>Price</hi> I heard the firſt aſperſion, that ever I heard of my ſelf, and it vvas thus,</p>
            <p>Standing in Cornhill, at a Book-ſellers ſhop, a man comes and looks me very earneſtly in my face, I took little regard to it and went away, I was no ſooner gone, but ſayes he to the Book ſeller, you are acquainted withall the ſparcks in the town; ſparcks ſaies he, the man ſeemes to be a rational man: I But replied the party, <hi>I</hi> am told he is a notorious drunkard, and a whore maſter, and that he painted his face, but I ſee thats falſe: whereupon the Book-ſeller having ſome knowledge of me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came troubled on my behalf; and fell to be very ſerious with him, to know his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, and he honeſtly tells him, naming this Mr. <hi>Price</hi> a mercer; and the Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller ſoon after tells me the whole ſtory, and the authors name, ſaying, he had been
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:44414:9"/> abuſed himſelf with baſe reports; and a man might be undone by them, and never know it, till t'was too late, and therefore had reſolved to hear no evil of any man, but if he could he would learn the au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hor, and tell the party concerned of it: this Book ſeller is Mr. <hi>Peter Cole</hi> at the ſign of the Printing preſſe, and I eſteem my ſelf obliedged to him, ever ſince for his plain dealing:</p>
            <p>So away went <hi>I</hi> to this Mr. <hi>Price,</hi> for I was ſomewhat troubled having never heard, evil of my ſelf till then: and I found him at Mr. <hi>Hilſlies,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a friendly manner made him acquainted, with my buſineſſe; he did not deny but he had ſpoken as much; and that walking in <hi>Weſtminiſter hall,</hi> he was called from me, and bid beware of me for I was ſuppoſed to be a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and a dangerous man: but he had not ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken any evil of me, as beleeving any of it to be true? ſo I told him he and I had come acquainted upon a very honeſt buſineſſe; about the remonſtrance preſented to the Common-councel, and therefore why he ſhould ſuffer ſuch words to paſſe from him concerning me; I did wonder at it; I told him how with very little en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry he might ſoon have been ſatisfied, that I was no ſuch man; aſkt him if he knew any at <hi>Garlick-hill,</hi> where I had lived fifteen yeers together, in good and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt repute; and where he ought to have informed himſelf; and not ſo unadviſedly to diſparage me: he ſeemed to be ſorry for it: ſo I only deſired him to let me know his author, he told me I muſt excuſe him; he might not do it: nor could I ever get him to tell me: ſo being familiar with my then friend Mr. <hi>Brandiff,</hi> I aſkt, whether they had not ſome rule, or method in their Church, to give a man ſome ſatisfaction, that had received palpable injury by a meraber; come ſaid he I know where abouts you mean; trouble not your ſelf, no body beleeves it: and this was all I could get in this caſe: wherein I yet ſtand injured, and ſince they are ſo deſirous, more then truth ſhould be beleeved of me: I think it fit this which is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly true, ſhould be known of their dealing with me.</p>
            <p>Nor can any ingenious people now blame me, for being thus open, and particuler, ſince this ſort of independents have made thus bold with my good name ſo long a time; and ſince it is evident that manifeſtation dated the 14 of <hi>April</hi> 1649. Publiſhed by my ſelf, and my other three fellow ſufferers; that I was willing to have vindicated my ſelf, from thoſe common reproaches, they had aſpert me withall without naming, or reflecting upon any perſon, or any ſort of men whatſoever, ſo carefull have I ever been, as much as in me is to have peace withall men; bearing, and forbearing to my own loſſe, rather then <hi>I</hi> would return evi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for evil.</p>
            <p>But their mallic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> breaking thus fouly out upon me, in this vile book; I ſhould be unjuſt to my ſelf, if I ſhould not do my beſt endeavour to manifeſt ſo deteſtable falſeneſſe, uttered to ſo bad an end, in ſo unſeemly a time (the time of my affliction) which I ſhall do with as much truth, as I can remember, profe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſing withall from my very heart, and conſcience, that I take no more pleaſure in doing of it, then I ſhould do in gathering up, and throwing away <hi>Snakes,</hi> and <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rmin</hi> ſcattered in my Garden; and do wiſh withall my ſoul they had not neceſſitated me, nor my other fellow-priſoners, to have exceeded our joynt <hi>Manifeſtation;</hi> but that we might all have been good friends thereupon.</p>
            <p>In which <hi>Manifeſtation,</hi> is to be ſeen all our very hearts, and wherein all our four heads, and hands were nigh equally employed, though this c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pritious author (Mr. <hi>John Price,</hi> its ſaid) be pleaſed to ſuppoſe me to be all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all therein; yet I muſt, and truly profeſſe the contrary: and muſt be bold to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell them, where my friend Lieutement Collonel <hi>John Lillburn,</hi> appeares otherwiſe in any of his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:44414:9"/> 
               <hi>I</hi> do not impute it to paſſion, as his adverſaries politiquely are accuſtomed; to take weak people off from the conſideration of what he ſays: but unto his zeal againſt that injuſtice, cruelty, hypocriſie, arrogancy, and flattery, which he hath found amongſt a ſort of men, from whom of any men in the world, he expected the contrary virtues; being otherwiſe to my knowledge, and upon experience, a very lamb in converſation; and whom goodneſſe, and love, and piety, juſtice, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, ſhall as ſoon melt, and that into tears (I hope he will pardon my blabbing) as any man in the world: but he hates all kinde of baſeneſſe, with a perfect hatred: eſpecially that of ingratitude, which he hath found, I have heard him ſay, ſo exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all meaſure, in ſome of the ſubſcribers of this pamphlet, that it loathes him to think of it.</p>
            <p>And as for my friend, Mr. <hi>Prince,</hi> whom this ſelf-conceited author, would make ſo weak in judgment, as to have no ability towards ſuch a work; it is his unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to be ſo exceedingly miſtaken; yet I muſt tell him, he hath given him ſo true a character, for honeſty, and ſincerity of heart, towards the publick, which in my eſteem, doth more commend him; then if he had attributed to him, all thoſe parts &amp; abilities, he falſly, and for an ill end, doth unto me: lifting me up to heaven, that he might caſt me down to hell: making me an Angel, that he might make me a Devil: which parts are more abounding in himſelf, as is to be ſeen in this his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Book, and for which he will one day ſigh and groan, except he make a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter uſe of them.</p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>John Price,</hi> Mr. <hi>Prince</hi> hath not a congregation to cry up his parts; amongſt whom there is ſuch a humor of flattery, as is not to be found the like again amongſt any ſort of men; Oh ſuch a Sermon, ſuch a diſcourſe, ſuch arguments, as never was heard of; when often times 'tis meer lamp-work, and ink horn termes; ſuch as the three firſt yeers in the Univerſity; or the firſt yeer of a ſound conſideration, with a ſincere conſcience, would be aſhamed of,</p>
            <p>But were Mr. <hi>Prince</hi> of one of your congregation, &amp; had but run with the ſtream, and turned with the times, as moſt of you have done; could he but have changed his principles with his condition; would he (as he was tempted by ſome of you) have belyed his friends, &amp; betrayed his cauſe, Oh what a man of parts Mr. <hi>Prince</hi> had been; what could Mr. <hi>Prince</hi> have wanted, that thoſe men had to give: but to their ſhame, let them know, Mr. <hi>Prince</hi> values the integrity of his conſcience above his life, or any thing in this world; and for which he deſerveth the love of all ſound hearted men.</p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>John Price,</hi> you that make it ſo ſtrange a thing for any man, to own in the ſubſtance, what another hath penn'd; there is a book with Mr. <hi>John Prices</hi> name at it, of no long date; and the ſubject of it is about the King-ſhip of the People: to me it ſeems, not to be the ſtile of Mr. <hi>John Price:</hi> I am againſt examin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you, upon queſtions againſt your ſelf; but there are (Knaves and Fools in Folio, a book ſo called) that ſeems to claim kindred of Mr. <hi>John Price</hi> in that peice; and if you be but a God-father; (and it be now againſt your judgement to be ſuch) yet ſince the childe beares your name, and tis a pretty handſome one, be not aſhamed ſtill to own it; but if you be, the childe ſhall not want, I'le undertake to finde the right Father: ſo much for Mr. <hi>Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for the complexion of my Friend Mr <hi>Overtons</hi> pen, truly it commonly car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſo much truth and reaſon in it, though ſometimes in a Comick, and otherwhiles in a Satyrick ſtile, that I do not wonder you ſhun its acquaintance; and you did wiſely by this touch and glance, think to paſſe him by without provoking of him:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:44414:10"/> But look to your ſelves, and ſay, I gave you lawfull warning; for he, I aſſure ye, knows when, and when not, to anſwer ſuch as you according to your folly: And truly, but that it is againſt the nature of impudence to bluſh, the complexion of the pen engaged in this your unſeemly diſcourſe, might well turn Cowler, in correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his: but he is old enough, let him anſwer for himſelf.</p>
            <p>But why come their lines from them, as through a Priſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, Mr <hi>Price?</hi> Are Priſons, in your Divinity, ſuch ominous things? The Primitive Chriſtians, and the Martyrs in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> daies, did not eſteem them ſo. But it ſeems your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation is of a near relation to thoſe that hold proſperity a mark of the true Church; and it will be good for thoſe amongſt you, that are yet ſincere in their Conſciences, in time to conſider it, and to enquire amongſt all thoſe Churches the Apoſtles wrote to, where they find a Warrant for ſuch ſlanderous and backbiting practiſes as you are accuſtomed unto, licking up the very foam and dregs of Mr <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> his <hi>Gangrena;</hi> yea, your own vomit and poyſon which then you caſt out up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him.</p>
            <p>But, I confeſſe, you have notable waies to eſcape impriſonments; you can be for a Kingly Government, and publiſh to all the world, that Kings are, as the Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Corn, not to be reapt by any humane fickle; and when occaſion ſerves, you can change your copy, and ſay, you are not bound to declare why your judgment alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: But pray, Mr <hi>Goodwin,</hi> are you not bound to undeceive thoſe whom by your errour you deceived, as ſoon as you ſaw your errour? Sometime your ſtrength is not in an arm of fleſh, nor in the power of the Sword, but you no ſooner get, as you think, the leaſt hold of it, but the power of the Sword is then the power of God, and then the Saints (meaning no body but your ſelves) muſt judge and rule the earth. Indeed Friends, you manifeſt to all the world, that your waies are the waies rather to good Offices and Benefices too (for elſe, why are ye now ſo high for tyths, that ſome years ſince were ſo much againſt them?) and le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to honours, and preferments, and greetings in the market places, rather then to priſons.</p>
            <p>Yet are ye furniſht with waies enough to ſend other men thither; you have one way, is called, <hi>Ah Lord! we thank thee we are not as other men:</hi> A way to make them firſt odious, by vindicating your ſelves in thoſe things whereof <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o man ſuſpected you, that others might be thought guilty; as you endeavoured by your Declaration, wherein you vindicated your ſelves from being <hi>againſt Magiſtracy,</hi> or liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, nor for Poligamy, or Community; and this in a time when you had freſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; falſely aſperſt us, to be oppoſite to you in all theſe, purpoſely to get your Guard into the Tower: and for your abatement, it will not be amiſſe to let you know how a weak woman anſwered your ſtrength ſpent in this elaborate Declaration, at firſt and in the reading of it; but it was my Wife, and ſhe having been (as you will have it) a Jeſuit's wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e this two and twenty years, may have more wit then ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary.</p>
            <p>Saies ſhe, <hi>They againſt Magiſtracy? Who can ſuſpect them, that hunt and ſeek for Offices as they do</hi> (now I am ſure the City and Cuſtome-houſe wil cry, <hi>probatum eſt)</hi> and where you argued your ſelves to be for liberty of Conſcience, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es ſhe, <hi>Who have more need?</hi> I <hi>am ſure none uſe ſo great a liberty, to raiſe ſuch vile and falſe reports as they do</hi> (for ſhe hears all you ſay of me, and about that time, that ſome of your tribe ſhould report I uſed her very hardly, and uſed to beat her; whereas we both know and believe in our conſciences, never two in the world lived more comfortably toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then we have done, nor have more delighted in one another.) And where you declared, you did not hold it lawfull to have more Wives then one, ſaies ſhe, <hi>They</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:44414:10"/> 
               <hi>that keep their Wives a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch a rate as they do, had not need to have more then one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peice, they will find one enough:</hi> And where you declared, that you were not for to have all things common, ſaies ſhe, <hi>No, I warrant you they know well enough how to hold their own: are not ſome of them <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurers?</hi> And you know it to be true: but if you deny it, we will find you for this alſo a <hi>probatum;</hi> and thus was your mighty <hi>Siſera</hi> ſtruck through the temples by the hand of a ſilly Woman: The truth is, ye over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ween your ſelves exceedingly, becauſe ye are a little ſkilfull in talking and writing: But why went ye not on boaſting? ye were no hypocrites, no ſlanderers, no back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biters, no envious, malicious perſons, no ſpies or intelligencers, no covetous or am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious perſons, no hard-hearted or cruell perſons: truly you took the better way to vindicate your ſelves of thoſe things only, that no men accuſed you of.</p>
            <p>Another way ye have to get men into priſon, by ſuggeſting fears and jealouſies of them into the minds of ſuch as are in power and authority; playing the pick-thanks by ſuch unworthy and uncharitable courſes; buzzing continually in their ears, that we drive on dangerous deſigns; that we are Atheiſts, Jeſuits, and the like, which hath been your common practice: inſomuch, as being with Collonel <hi>Martin,</hi> and another Gentleman, about a month before I was made a Priſoner, at Lieutenant Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>Cromwels;</hi> and amongſt other diſcourſe, wondering why he ſhould ſuffer me continually at his table to be reproacht, as if I were a Jeſuit, and a man of dangerous principles; whereas none in the world could have more teſtimony of any man to the contrary, then he had of me; and why he did not vindicate me, when he heard me ſo abuſed: he told me, that he could not believe thoſe ſcandals, that he had profeſt often and again he could not; but they were brought continually to them by Citizens, that were eſteemed honeſt godly men: And truly I do believe in my Conſcience, we never had been thus dealt withall as we are, but by your reports; and that we are priſoners more by your occaſion then any other.</p>
            <p>And what a way did Mr <hi>Kiffin,</hi> &amp; his Aſſociates, find out as ſoon as we were in, to ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet us in, with a Petition ſomewhat like your forementioned Declaration? The ſcope thereof being truly Phariſaicall: Another, <hi>Lord, we thank thee, we are not as other men, &amp;c. Nor as theſe Publicans-No Anabaptiſts of Munſter</hi> (defiling their own neſt) as ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that lying ſtory of that injured people true) <hi>and praying the Parliament to be carefull to ſuppreſſe all prophaneneſſe and licenciouſneſſe: as if we had been ſuch a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:</hi> But ſo juſtly did this miſchief (intended on us) turn on their own heads, that moſt of their own people abhorred the practice, as Un-Chriſtian; and Mr <hi>Thomas Lamb</hi> of the <hi>Spittle,</hi> offered to prove the promoters of it guilty of injuſtice, arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance, flattery and cruelty, and to give them a meeting to that purpoſe; but ſure they were aſham'd, and durſt not, for none of them would undertake him.</p>
            <p>Beſides theſe waies of holding Priſoners faſt, my back-friend, Mr <hi>Arnald,</hi> hath a way of going from houſe to houſe, to diſcover matter (there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing none at all in theſe very mens opinions of me) For they all conclude, <hi>England's New Chains,</hi> to be none of my indicting: I wonder why then they did not petition, or move for my enlargement. No, beſides that I am not of their Church; 'twas good holding a man ſo hardly to be catcht, that needed horſe and foot to catch and fetch him out of his bed: And therfore this Mr <hi>Arnald</hi> alſo ſends Spies to enſnare and entrap us in our diſcourſe: and for encouragement to thoſe he ſends, that they may not ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but think they do God good ſervice therein; he proſeſſes continually, I am a Jeſuit: And now, I believe, finding his errour (for it's very eaſily found) he dreads
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:44414:11"/> my releaſment, as believing I may have remedy at Law for ſo deſtructive a ſlander: and therfore hath thought even to overwhelm me with this floud of aſperſions, that I ſhould not poſſibly eſcape drowning. But the man's miſtaken, and ſo are his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bettors and Aſſociates; 'tis but a Viſion, a falſe fantaſtick apparation; they are all Nothings, meer falſneſſes, Serpents of Magicians making, the meer works of a mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious imagination, that by croſſe working, forcing and wreſting of words and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, and by ſames and opinions, hath made a kind of crawling thing, that might poſſibly ſerve to fright Children, or to pleaſe a Church that would go a wool-gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for a miracle, to confirm its reallity: But <hi>truth,</hi> which is <hi>Moſes</hi> his Serpent, you ſhall ſee will eat them up, and devour them all: Many of them, if you well conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what you have here and elſwhere read, being conſumed already.</p>
            <p>That which remains in generall, is, that I aim at the deſtroying of Religion, and at the ſubverſion of all Government: But why ſhould I do either Where's the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage? I have alwaies profeſs'd the contrary, and ever practiſed the contrary; as thoſe that reade my <hi>Whiſper to Mr Edwards,</hi> and <hi>my ſtill and ſoft voyce,</hi> fore-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, will eaſily believe. And I begge and intreat both young and old to reade them, before they give ſentence in their own hearts of me, that I ſhould be ſo irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, as to utter ſuch profane language concerning the Book of Pſalms, or Proverbs, or that horrid expreſſion of the Book of Canticles, as that it was nothing elſe but one of <hi>Salomons Epiphonemacs:</hi> a word that I never ſpake, nor yet know well how to pronounce, nor ever did apply the meaning of it to ſo vile an end (ſpeak the reſt, whoſo will for me) and if the Author had had any modeſty or Religion in him, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it had come into his thought, he would have ſilenc'd it, rather then ſuch bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphemy ſhould be ſeen in print; I abhor the words ſhould be in any of my paper; having never entred my thought, or paſt my lips.</p>
            <p>As true, likewiſe, are all the other unworthy paſſages in the 9 and 10 pages of that ſhameleſſe book; they have been all malicious ſnatchings and gatherings from ſome officious tongues, at third, fourth or tenth hand; there being nothing but miſtakes and miſ-applications in all of them, contrary to my judgment, or any thing ever intended by me, in my diſcourſe of any of thoſe ſubjects: And to ſhew ſome palpable token, that they are meer malicious ſmatterings, I appeal to all that know me, whether ever I were heard to commend <hi>Plutarch's Morals</hi> to any mans reading; it being a Book, that although I have had above theſe twenty years, yet I am cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, I never read forty hours therein; though I ſomewhat blame my ſelf for my neglect, it being ſo generally commended by wiſe and judicious men: yet I could never perſwade my ſelf to take the pains in reading of it, it being ſomewhat too <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious for my expectation. And as for <hi>Cicero</hi>'s Orations, I never had it; have only ſeen it; and (though very unadviſedly, as I was lately told by one whoſe judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I love) am ſomewhat prejudic'd againſt his writings, as eſteem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng him a verball and vain-glorious Writer.</p>
            <p>I have, indeed, bemoaned the breeding of the Youth of this Nation, as being bred ſo, as to be artificiall and crafty, rather then truly wiſe and honeſt; to be Sophiſters, and Pedantick Diſputers, and Wranglers about words, then of ſolid judgment: but as for feats of activity, it's a light expreſſion, to be applyed rather <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o tumblers, and the like, then to be a part of Childrens breeding; and for Geometry, there may be much in it, and of uſe: but I have not ſo much ſkill in it, as that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> could make it matter for my commendation. So that theſe Intelligencers being engaged in evil
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:44414:11"/> deſigns, and knowing themſelves guilty, are confuſed in their thoughts, their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences ever flying in their faces; and ſo they hear otherwiſe then is uttered, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port different from what they hear, and ſo prove by a juſt providence deſtructive to thoſe that employ them; and it were pity an ill end ſhould be better ſerved.</p>
            <p>In the 11 page, becauſe he would not want matter to diſparage, he puls in I know not who, that, forſooth, muſt be of my acquaintance, and ſpeaking abſurd pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane language, concerning things heavenly, and of God; that I profeſſe I do not think any man in the world would utter, nor think them fit to be repeated, much leſſe printed, to ſave a life: whereas this unhappy Author puts them in a particular character, leſt they ſhould paſſe un-obſerved; and that not to ſave, but to deſtroy me and mine: Who this ſhould be, I cannot gheſſe; but it ſeems, it is a man of parts, poſſibly, for to have made him an intelligencer: if ſo you have given him your reward, ſlander him, and let him go; and 'tis well he ſcapes ſo, as the world goes.</p>
            <p>For there are uſes for Spies and Intelligencers, that few men dream of; and Mr <hi>John Price,</hi> and Mr <hi>Goodwin,</hi> and Mr <hi>Lavander,</hi> knows of the making of them, their inſtructions and oaths of employment and ſecrecy; an office and inſtitution we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver read of in all the New Teſtament: but what wonder if their practice be point-Blanck againſt the Scriptures, whoſe ſtructure is not built upon (but borrowed, or rather forc'd upon) that golden foundation?</p>
            <p>As for the next paſſage in the 11 page, that I ſhould affirm the Scriptures to be, and not to be the Word of God; it is ſuch a double way of expreſſion, as I diſlike in all men, and avoyd it in all my writings or diſcourſe: but-for this, or any thing relating to the Scriptures, I refer the honeſt-hearted Reader to my <hi>ſtill and ſoft voyce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that I ſhould perſwade that Gentlewoman next mentioned, to ruine her ſelf, is as falſe as ever was ſpoken, as her Huſband, her Siſters, her Friend that was continually with her, her Servants and Children, I am confident are all ready to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie, and ſome of them I am certain will witneſſe, that I uſed my utmoſt ſkill to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade her, and did manifeſt as much grief for her, as I never did more for any, except a Child I had, to whom ſhe was Godmother, for ſhe was my true Friend, and her Huſband hath for theſe twelve years (as I have cauſe to believe) held me as dear to him as any Friend, and ſo hath continued to the time I came into priſon; and her ſiſter that hath been in the moſt extreme affliction for her, hath yet ſhewed ſo much reſpect to me (with the Gentlewoman that was alwaies with my diſtreſſed Friend) as to give me a viſit in this my impriſonment, and ſo alſo hath two of her Sons: theſe are truths, and will be believed by all that truly knew both her and me; though Mr <hi>Goodwins</hi> whole Church ſhould ſwear the contrary; and from whom ſhe deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a better regard. I am ſorry their hate to me ſhould awake the remembrance of that ſad diſaſter from ſleep, where it ought to have reſted; ſhe being very religious after the way of Mr <hi>Simpſon</hi> of <hi>Allhallowes Thames-ſtreet,</hi> and no admirer of Mr <hi>John Goodwin:</hi> Inſomuch as it was ſaid to her, in her greateſt extremity of pain in her head (the greateſt, in my apprehenſion, and moſt continued, that ever was felt) you have a wiſe Religion, that cannot bear with a pain in your head: his profeſſion that ſaid it, required another remedy; but as he exceeded in his tongue, he was as ſhort in his brain and hand: Not only ſhe, but her Huſband to this hour, being much di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſt through ſuch comforters: and it were well ſome ſkilfull man would adminiſter
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:44414:12"/> ſome matter to cure the man of his vain-glory, and flaſhing ſelf conceitedneſſe, with which he abounds to the deſtruction of ſome native goodneſſe, &amp; acquired parts; which would otherwiſe commend him: I could not be more particular in this ſtory, leſt I ſhould grieve my friends, who I know cannot but deſire this were bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in oblivion.</p>
            <p>As falſe alſo is that other paſſage, concerning King <hi>James,</hi> and King <hi>David:</hi> it having never been my manner, to uſe ſuch opprobious language towards any men; much leſſe towards perſons of ſuch Eminency, but Generally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proove it.</p>
            <p>I have from a ſerious conſideration of <hi>Davids</hi> offences, and Gods paſſing them by, and not rejecting of him for them; obſerved a different way from God, in thoſe of our times, that call themſelves Saints, and would be eſteemed his neareſt ſervants; for if any man be overtaken in a fault; they are ſo far from reſtoring ſuch a one by the ſpirit of meekneſſe: or, reproving him privatly, or by love, as Gods way is; paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing by multitudes of ſins, and ſailings; that they make it their meat and drink, yea, they hunger, and thirſt after evil reports; yea, ſend out into the high-wayes, and hedges, and as it were compell men to come in to witneſſe, and article, againſt men too, that have hazarded their lives for their good: and with whom they have frequently, familiarly, and intimately converſed; never reproveing them in their lives to their faces: and keep things in boxes, three, four, ſix, yeers together, watching a ſeaſon to divulge them to their ruin: as now in mine, &amp; my friends caſes.</p>
            <p>They that are now advocates for <hi>David,</hi> if <hi>David</hi> lived in our dayes, and had not favoured Mr. <hi>Goodwins</hi> Church-way, and had been guilty of the matter with <hi>Bath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheba,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi> where ſhould <hi>David</hi> have found a place to have hid himſelf, who amongſt them; (according to their preſent rule with us) wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d have pleaded for him? nay, had not <hi>Davids</hi> wiles (pardon the expreſſion) been publiſhed in words at length, and not in figures: yet poſſibly (nay probably) <hi>Davids</hi> being King had alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the caſe with theſe men; eſpecially, if he were ſupream in power: for they are ever carefull to row with, or not long againſt the tide: but what (think you) would they not give that they had ſuch <hi>matter</hi> againſt me, that make ſo much to gather up falſe <hi>reports</hi> againſt me; what ſociety ſhould I keep; who would own me, no marvail? now I ſee, that <hi>David</hi> being put to his choice; choſe rather to fall into the hands of God, then into the hands of men: for with him there is mercy, his mercies are over all his works; he delighteth in ſhewing mercy, he conſiders that we are but duſt: and putteth away our ſins out of his remembrance; as far as the Eaſt is from the Weſt: whereas the mercies of men are cruelties: although I cannot ſo experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally ſay it, of any other ſort of men, as of theſe; for I have found the contrary from ſo many other ſorts of people, upon divers of my particular occaſions, that I have wondered to conſider the difference.</p>
            <p>For the next ſlander: that I ſhould ſpeak ſo ſlightly, of the ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt; this I heard they have aſperſt me with all above theſe three yeers: and I have conſidered it ſeriouſly, and can profeſſe, with a ſincere conſcience, that I do not know that I ever uttered a ſyllable towards it: ſure I am it never entred into my heart: nor could I, till now I ſee it in their book, learn, to what woman they char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged me to have ſpoken it: but yet becauſe I gheſſed, they might mean the gentle-wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man forementioned, ſhe being well known to them: I have told her of the aſpertion; and deſired ſeriouſly if ſhe could to call to minde, whither ever any ſuch unadviſed ſpeech had paſt from me to her; as I might meete her, and in a friendly manner chide her for not viſiting my wife: and ſhe hath very often ſolemnly proteſted, ſhe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:44414:12"/> could not for her life remember, that I did ever ſpeake any thing towards it: and truly, if I had known any ſuch thing by my ſelf, though it had been never ſo unſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, I ſhould have taken the ſhame of it to my ſelf; and have manifeſted my ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for it, as not in the leaſt juſtifying a careleſnes in things of ſo high a nature: and do fear, they come neer to ſcoffing, that dare thus liberally publiſh in print, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions ſo unſutable to ſo divine a ſubject, for they may remain upon a readers mind, to prejuduce, longer then he would have them.</p>
            <p>And concerning the next ſlander; I might blame her for her ſadneſſe, and fear, which ſometimes ſhe would expreſſe, as being contrary to the principle, of that love of God, ſhe would conſtantly profeſſe, to have aſſurance of: urging frequently that place, which ſaith, we have not received the ſpirit of bondage to fear any more; but the ſpirit of adoption whereby we cry, <hi>Abba, Father;</hi> and have boldneſſe to the throne of Grace, and the like; but that I ever diſcouraged her in the hearing of Mr. <hi>Simpſon;</hi> or in the wayes of religion, I utterly deny,</p>
            <p>And being thus, as thus in truth it is, and no otherwiſe in all the perticulars forementioned; let all impartiall, and judicious people judge, whether it had not been more for the honour of God, the Scriptures and Religion; that this authour; his aſſociats ſubſcribers, his abetters, and confederates; to have received in good part our clear <hi>manifeſtation;</hi> wherein we juſtly vindicated our ſelves in generall, from thoſe aſperſions that cauſleſly were caſt upon us; without naming any perſon, or perſons, as authors thereof; or reflecting, with the leaſt rancour upon any conditon of men; as being willing, if poſſible, to have buried for ever, all former unkindneſſes, and evill offices done to any of us in this kinde: and as far as in us was to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed our former friendſhip with thoſe, in whom we had formerly delighted, or at leaſt to have expelled that enmity, which we knew was exceedingly prejudiciall to the Common-wealth: I ſay, had it not been much more Chriſtian-like; then to have ſet their brains, and credits thus upon the tenters (ſtretching them paſt the ſtaple that they will never in again) and to put upon record, ſo many unſeemly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, as if they gladly took accaſion through my ſides, &amp; friends, to give Religion, the ſcriptures; yea, God himſelf were it poſſible a deadly wound: for ſuch I fear will be the effect; whither throw their malice, or indiſcretion, or both, I leave to judgment: and for what cauſe, at beſt; but only to render me and my friends odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, to diſcredit us in the things we undertook for the publick.</p>
            <p>And then to cry out of violence in ſome mens writings, and yet to abound, as here they do, with ſuch new invented invectives, and provoking language, as is hardly to be parallel'd: <hi>Cheef ſecretaries of the Prince of ſlander:</hi> this <hi>Engliſh man-hunter, this wretch:</hi> this, <hi>wretched man Walwyn:</hi> this <hi>worthy Champion: the veniſon, which his ſoul doth ſo ſorely long for: as the ſerpent, that deceived our firſt Parents: this factor for the Region of Darkneſſe, theſe Jeſuiticall-whifflers: this artificall impoſtor, in his Satan-like work:</hi> Good God, where is the cauſe, what hath moved them to this high flown mallice, theſe bumbaſte poetick raptures, fit rather for ſtagers; then Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, for ſwagg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rers, then Saints, (oh, but it muſt not be ſo taken; it muſt be eſteemed their zeal, their <hi>Jehu</hi>-like affection to God, and his truth; yea, come ſee our zeal (ſay they in effect) which we have for God: why, be it ſo, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Jehu,</hi> yet what's the cauſe?</p>
            <p>The cauſe; why, heers <hi>Walwyn</hi> with his <hi>Wiles</hi> will overturn, deſtroy, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw all Religion; and the Scriptures themſelves? ſure its not poſſible? no, have you ever heard ſuch things uttered by man, as is recited in <hi>Walwyns Wiles?</hi> no, but he denies them to be true; gives reaſons here; and refers to his <hi>Whiſper:</hi> and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:44414:13"/> other writings: and particularly to his ſtill, and ſoft voice: and thoſe are extant, and to be ſeen; and ſurely if he intend to deſtroy Religion, to publiſh ſuch things as theſe is not the way; beſides, uttered by one, that you your ſelves ſay is wary, and ſober, and diſcreet. But I pray, friends what a religion is yours, that fears the breath of one man ſhould overthrow it? what? is it built upon the ſand? if ſo, you may doubt indeed; but if upon a rock? let the winds blow, and the waves too-beat; what need you fear? ſure your faith is built but upon Reaſon; look to it; ſome ſay it is your tenent; if ſo, you had need indeed to be ſtir your ſelves, for you finde he is a rationall man, and thats a ſhew'd thing; againſt <hi>Diana</hi> of the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> though all <hi>Aſia,</hi> &amp; the world worſhip her: if your Churches have but an imaginary foundation then indeed you had need betake your ſelves to <hi>Demetrius</hi> his Arguments; and to tell all men? theſe <hi>Walwynites</hi> every where, turn the world upſide down; breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtrange, and unwelcome doctrines, ſuch as your Churches and people cannot bear.</p>
            <p>And ſo it ſeems, indeed they do, as theſe authors Complain in the latter part of their 13 pag. where they ſay, I <hi>am ever harping upon the hard-heartednes and uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritablenes</hi> of profeſſors; <hi>and thoſe that are religious men, how grinding they are in bargines: how pennurious: baſe, and back ward in works of charity, and mercy, how undermining, and over-reaching they are in buying, in ſelling; how having and craving in the things of this life; how hardly any work of mercy, and charity comes from them; how they let their brethren ſtarve, and dy, and periſh, rather then help them; and how bountifull, free, and liberall the very heathens have been and how beneficiall even Popiſts, and many that do not ſo much, as pretend to religion, are to the poor; and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in (he confeſſeth)</hi> I <hi>ſpeake too true:</hi> yet immediately calls me devil for my labour they pay their Paſtors better, I beleeve, for worſe doctrine)</p>
            <p>But why devil? Why, ſay they, for ſpeaking truth to wound, and deſtroy it; but ſay I, who art thou, ô man, that judgeſt another mans Conſcience, forbear the chair a while, &amp; it may be the chair of the ſcornful: for God and my own conſcience knows, I never yet in my life ſpake, or uttered one of theſe truthes but to the end the Scriptures warrant.</p>
            <p>But they go further, and ſay, by doing thus, I cunningly inſinua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e into the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcreet, and beget a diſparagement of <hi>that that is called Religion amongſt them.</hi> page the 14.</p>
            <p>This is very obſervable: for by this expreſſion, all men ſhall eaſily underſtand the ground of their quarrell againſt me: if they can but finde out, <hi>what it is that is called Religion amongſt them:</hi> do not theſe men call ſuch a thing Religion; as the <hi>Phariſes</hi> did; Ile deal ſo kindly with them, yet; as to leave the comparing the one with the other to themſelves: only, <hi>'twas much in words, and to be ſeen of men:</hi> both which our Saviour reproves: and both by example, and precept invites to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice; poſſitively concluding, that not he that ſaith Lord, Lord; ſhall enter into the kingdom, but he that <hi>doth</hi> the will of my father which is in heaven: requireth, That our light ſo ſhine forth before men, that they, ſeeing <hi>our good works,</hi> may glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie our heavenly father and at the laſt day, he will ſay unto thoſe on his right hand, Come ye bleſſed of my Father, receive the kingdom prepared for you; for when I was an hungry, ye fed me, naked, ye clothed me; ſick and in priſon, and ye viſited me; in as much as ye have done it unto theſe, ye have done it unto me: when to others, (that yet have to ſay, <hi>Lord</hi> we have propheſied, and done many great things in thy name) he will ſay; Away from me ye workers of iniquity, I know ye not, for when I was hungry, ye ſed me not: naked, ye clothed me not; ſick and in priſon, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:44414:13"/> ye viſited me not; inaſmuch as ye did it not unto theſe, ye did it not unto me.</p>
            <p>And if now to invite to theſe, and to reprove the want thereof, be, to be a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, truly I'l bear it, and rejoyce that I am accounted worthy to ſuffer reproach for this cauſe of Chriſt: I am ſure the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> (that abounded with reall, not pretended gifts, or acquiſitions rather) boaſted not of them; but proclaims to all the world, that though he ſpake with the tongues of men and Angels, and have no Charity, that he was but as ſounding braſſe, or a tinkling Cymball; and Saint <hi>James,</hi> his pure and undefiled Religion, is, to viſit the fatherleſſe, and the widowes in their diſtreſſe, and to keep our ſelves unſpotted of the world; and ſaith plainly, that he who hath this worlds goods, and ſeeth his brother lack, and ſhutteth up his bowels of compaſſion, how dwelleth the love of God in him? And truly, if I muſt be a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil for inſiſting upon theſe moſt needfull doctrines, I had rather be theſe mens De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil then their Saint: And if the uſe and application of theſe, and the like, will over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw that which they call Religion amongſt them; certainly it is not pure and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled, and hardly of Gods making: I might enlarge my ſelf upon this theme, but the little Book, called, <hi>The vanity of the preſent Churches,</hi> hath prevented me, unto which I refer the ingenious Reader, for ſatisfaction of what <hi>they call Religion among them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus I think to all unbiaſſed men, I have acquitted my ſelf from going about to deſtroy Religion; <hi>I</hi> mean, true, not falſe Religion, or ſuperſtition, too common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dignified with the title of Religion.</p>
            <p>And as for my deſigning, as the deſire of my ſoul, the trouble, miſery and ruine of this Commonwealth, it is ſo abſurd a ſuggeſtion, that it ſeems not worth my anſwer; the utmoſt of my deſire concerning this Commonwealth, being held forth and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the <hi>Agreement of the People,</hi> dated the firſt of <hi>May,</hi> 1649. And as a teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of our acquieſcence therein, is ſubſcribed by Lieut: Col: <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> Mr <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Overton,</hi> Mr <hi>Thomas Prince,</hi> and my ſelf: ſo that all my deſigns are therein center'd; and if that imports the trouble, miſery and ruine of this Commonwealth, I am extremely miſtaken, and ſhall not refuſe to acknowledge my errour when I ſee it: but till then, and whil'ſt I conceive it to tend to the good of all men, I cannot but wiſh it might be eſtabliſh'd with contentment and ſecurity of all ſorts of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: I know not the man in the world, whoſe finger I deſire ſhould ak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> longer then he pinches another; nor that any man ſhould be reduced to any extremity, by any alteration it might bring with it: but that authority would provide rather a change of intereſts, and remove men from that which is not, to that which is conſiſtent with the peace, freedom and proſperity of the Nation; it having been all along a ſad thing to me, to ſee men of parts, and breeding, and eminency, upon reformation of intereſts, or their reducements, to be left to the wide world, without any care or regard of a livelyhood for themſelves, their Wives and Children, in ſome meaſure anſwerable to their former condition: ſuch extremities commonly begetting grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and more miſchievous to the Commonwealth; and it ſhould, in my poor opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, be the care of the ſupreme Authority; no deſire being more forcible in man, then to live anſwerable to his breeding, or to what he hath been long accuſtomed; every one finding it an eaſie thing to learn how to abound, but to abate, moſt diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult: and, I fear, our late and preſent times ſuffer much under theſe two ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremes.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:44414:14"/>
            <p>He upbraids me, that I find fault, that riches, and eſtates, and the things of this world, ſhould prefer men to offices, and places of truſt: but ſay that virtue, though in poor men, ſhould be more regarded, as in Butchers, or Coblers: And truly I know ſome Butchers, though not many, as fit as ſome in your Congregations; and I think you do not exclude for that trade: And as for Coblers, there are trades more in credit, hardly ſo uſefull, and Mr <hi>Price</hi> knows it well; and were he as buſy in ſelf examination, as he is in reproaching others, he would have little time to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble himſelf about others motes: he who thought it no robbery to be equall with God, and yet deſpiſed not to be eſteemed the Son of a Carpenter, and choſe ſimple herdſmen for his Prophets, and poor fiſhermen for his Apoſtles, did certainly judge otherwiſe then theſe Churchmen judge. Beſides, there was a time, when <hi>Samuel How,</hi> a Cobler by trade, and a contented man in that calling, was not aſhamed to preach before your moſt learned Paſtor, and printed his Sermon afterwards; and your Paſtor hath chang'd his mind ſince, and is come ſomewhat neare to his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and had done then, as is ſaid, and can be proved, could any have ſhewed him a livelyhood with credit, upon the exchange.</p>
            <p>But by the way, I am not ſo ſtrong as to talk uſually after this rule. I know the generality of our times cannot bear it; I indulge exceedingly towards the weakneſs of men for peace ſake: who ever heard me ſpeak either in behalf of Butchers or Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, as to places of government? I profeſſe, I know not where, nor when; though for their callings, I make no difference between them and my ſelf; for the callings are honeſt, and mine can but be ſo.</p>
            <p>And as for Riches, Saint <hi>James,</hi> whom I am exceeding in love with had no great good opinion thereof: he demands poſitively, Do not rich men oppreſſe you, and leade you before the Magiſtrates? (the Magiſtrates, poſſibly, were no rich men) Nay, is there not ſuch an expreſſion again in Scripture, as, Go too, weep and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owl, ye rich men, &amp;c? But I ſhall be told anon, I have too much ſtraw for this brick; truly, I wiſh I had none at all, and that you and your Aſſociates had been more adviſed, then to have neceſſitated me thus to diſcover your weakneſſe; but I comfort my ſelf, that I ſhall turn it to your good. I hope you will ſay no more, that by theſe truths I ſhall deſtroy that which is called <hi>Religion amongſt you,</hi> for this is a part of pure and undefiled Religion: And if you make one more change, and ſell all that ever you have, all your uncertainties, vanities, and ſuperfluities, for theſe reallities, it will prove the beſt bargain that ever you made; and, I believe, we ſhould be Friends upon it; this difference being the only quarrell: And that Riches may no longer be a ſtumbling block in your way, reade, at your leiſure, <hi>Montaign</hi>'s 52 Chapter, of the Parcimony of our Fore-Fathers.</p>
            <p>And where you charge me, that I find fault that ſome abound, whil'ſt others want bread; truly, I think it a ſad thing, in ſo fruitfull a land, as, through Gods bleſſing, this is; and I do think it one main end of Government, to provide, that thoſe who refuſe not labour, ſhould eat comfortably: and if you think otherwiſe, I think it your errour, and your unhappineſſe: But for my turning the world upſide down, I leave it to you, it's not a work I ever intended, as all my actions, and the Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the People, do ſufficiently evince, and doth indeed ſo fully anſwer all your remaining rambling ſcandals, that I ſhall pray the courteo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Reader hereof to reade it, and apply it, and then ſhall not doubt my full and clear vindication: ſo far as that is, am I for plucking up of all the pales and hedges in the Nation; ſo far, for all things common.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:44414:14"/>
            <p>So far from wiſhing printing had never been known, that I have alwaies ſaid, that printing (if any thing in this age) would preſerve us from ſlavery; and you that know how much I have been againſt the ſtopping of the preſſe, methinks ſhould bluſh to talk thus.</p>
            <p>As for Mr <hi>Pym,</hi> and Mr <hi>Hampden,</hi> it's well known, I honoured them much, for what I ſaw was good in them, and never reproach'd them in my life; but was not ſatisfied, when they would make a war, that they would make it in the name of the King and Parliament; I could not underſtand it to be plain dealing, nor thouſands more beſides me.</p>
            <p>As for any invectives againſt the Lieutenant Generall <hi>Cromwel,</hi> Commiſſary Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>Ireton,</hi> or Collonel <hi>Harriſon,</hi> I ſhall refer this to be ſatisfied by one Mr <hi>David Brown,</hi> the Scotch Writing-Maſter, a man of integrity, and of a ſincere Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, what I have done to the contrary: but I allow him not to be over-particular, in naming what particularly, that being inconvenient: And if Collonel <hi>Harriſon</hi> would but remember my attendance on him at Collonel <hi>Fleetwoods,</hi> and but reflect upon a paper I then deliver'd him, methinks my integrity to my Country, and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to all ſuch as deſire the liberty thereof, could not be queſtion'd; and, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, I have wondered, he of any man in power, hath not appeared more to my vindication: indeed, I have no fawning flattering waies to work upon men, nor have uſed any towards them, I have been reall and plain-hearted towards them; and though you may have courted them more plauſibly into an opinion of your way in the affairs of the Commonwealth; yet is it conſcience and time that proves all things, and I refer my ſelf to both; and if you prove not to them (and the reſt in power, that give ear to you) like <hi>Rhehoboam's</hi> young Counſellours, I ſhall be glad of it; I am ſure you came in late to the work, and (to my apprehenſion) labour to build hay and ſtubble, if not worſe, upon a golden foundation, laid by others for the Freedom of the Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>But I muſt beware, for, as I hear, you much rejoyce in a new Act concerning Treaſon; ſo copious, that I may be in the verge of it, before I am aware; it makes me almoſt not ſorry that I am kept cloſe Priſoner, but that it's no good ſign of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glands</hi> liberty which I have earneſtly labour'd for: but truly I may rejoyce that I am kept from you, and you from me; for certainly, ſhould we paſſe but one hours di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe together (in the mind you are in) and as the caſe and law now is, I ſhould not eſcape an information.</p>
            <p>And truly, that ye are ſo well pleas'd with this act proceeds, for that it ſerves your preſent turn, rather then any reaſon or conſideration in you; for how ſoon the edge of it may be turned againſt your ſelves, you know not; and ſome who conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der not how much ye have labour'd for it, wonder ye do not petition againſt it: for whil'ſt a Parliament ſits, it is lawfull to petition againſt things, though eſtabliſh'd by Law; and it's ſomewhat rare in the practice of Parliaments, for a law to take place, and be of force ſo ſoon as it is made, having commonly had a good diſtance of time, that men might diſgeſt, and conſider and underſtand it, before the commencement or beginning of the power thereof; and that, at ſooneſt, not before the end of the Parliament that made it: And there ſeems to be this reaſon for it, that the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment men that made it ſhould be as ſoon, and as clearly ſubject thereunto, as any other perſons whatſoever; otherwiſe they might make ſuch, as might enſnare the people, and yet keep themſelves out of danger.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:44414:15"/>
            <p>And certainly, if this caution be neceſſary in any caſe, it muſt be where mens lives are concerned, as in Treaſon and Felony; wherein our fore fathers were ever very carefull; as Sir <hi>Edward Cooke</hi> doth ſufficiently witneſſe, ſome particulars whereof concerning Treaſon, are worth yours, and every mans knowledge.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Briefly thus: he ſaies, The Parliament holden the 25th of <hi>Ed.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> was called <hi>benedictum Parliamentum;</hi> becauſe of its particular expreſſing what was Treaſon: and that except <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> no other Act of Parliament hath had more Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour given to it, as appeareth by the Statute of the 1 of <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. chap. 10. reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing, That whereat a Parliament, holden the 21 of <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. <hi>Divers paines of Treaſon were ordained by Statute, inſomuch as there was no man did know how to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have himſefe; to do, ſpeake, or ſay, for doubt of ſuch paines:</hi> It is enacted, &amp;c. <hi>That in no time to come, any Treaſon be judged otherwiſe, then it was ordained by the Statute of</hi> 25 Ed. 3. the like honour is given to it, by the Statute 1 <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. chap. 12. and by the Statute of the firſt of <hi>Mary,</hi> chap. 1. Seſſ. 1.—diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent times, but all agreeing in the magnifying, and extolling that bleſſed Act of 25 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And ſpeaking of the care of our Anceſtors, in avoiding nice and extreame Laws concerning Treaſon: he ſaith, <hi>And all this was done in ſeverall Ages, that the faire Lillies and Roſes of the Crowne (which now may be interpreted) the Government of</hi> England, <hi>might flouriſh, and not be ſtained with ſevere and ſanguinary (bloudy) Statutes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He ſaith further, That the Statute for Treaſon, is to be taken ſtrictly; and the <hi>proofs</hi> to be <hi>direct</hi> and <hi>manifeſt;</hi> not upon <hi>conjecturall preſumptions,</hi> or <hi>inferences,</hi> or <hi>ſtraines</hi> of <hi>Wit:</hi> but upon good and ſufficient proof, <hi>That none are to be procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt, but according to due courſe, and proceeding of Law, to be judged by men of our own condition; and not by abſolute power, or other meanes, as in former times had been uſed;</hi> and affirmes it to be a received maxim, that <hi>bare words with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an overt Act, could not make a Traytor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if you can rejoyce that theſe ſtrong holds, and ſafegards of our lives, ſhall now in the firſt year of <hi>Englands</hi> Liberty, with the Petition of Right, be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of no value; but that we muſt be ſo expoſed to danger, that no man ſhall know how to behave himſelfe, to doe, ſpeake, or ſay, for fear of the paines of Treaſon: I believe your rejoycing is but matter of grief to us, and the reſt of the plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted people in <hi>England:</hi> it being not <hi>who</hi> doth it, but <hi>what</hi> is done, that moſt concernes all men: you uſe to talke of ſomething ſtill, in the bottome of what I, and my friends propoſed; but when ſhall we ſee what lies at the bottome of your hearts, if ſuch as thoſe rejoycings are aflote already?</p>
            <p>You think it ſtrange, that we ſhould object againſt Martiall Law, in times of Peace, for Souldiers or others; and yet if you read the Petition of Right, you cannot but confeſſe it to be expreſly therein provided againſt; you deny us all Legall proceedings, and yet thinke the proceedings of the <hi>Swiſſe</hi> a horrible thing; a ſtory kept in Lavander about ſeven years, and next to one that now is not, is due to him that kept it in ſweetning ſo long, for ſo unſavoury a ſeaſon, and whoſe profeſſion is nearer cutting of throats, then mine is; and as I remember, was very merry at the thought of it.</p>
            <p>I am of opinion, there is much, if not more need of another kind of Law; and I could wiſh ſome good people would conſider of it, but I have no hope of your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation: <hi>It is a Law againſt Lying;</hi> you know what a ſad condition the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture holds ſorth to him that loveth, or maketh a lye: what thinke you of it? will our
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:44414:15"/> trades bear it? there needs no ſanguinary puniſhment be annexed, but ſome eaſie puniſhment: beſides, if you hear one that is not of your own Congregation aſperſt, and runne preſently and tell it to others, before you are certaine of the truth your ſelf, this need not paſſe for a lye, if you can but remember your author; though he had it only from the father of lies: being ſure alſo, that you may confidently a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouch, that you had it from a very pretious Godly man; ſo are all your Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: or if you do but thinke ye remember a thing right, and witneſſe it; this alſo had not need to be taken for a lie neither: and ſome ſuch other indulgences, as the time, and your occaſions require; there are ſome ſay, <hi>pia mendacia,</hi> thoſe that are Learned amongſt you, will expound the meaning; there may be a remiſſion alſo for thoſe, but certainly, yet a Law (though with allowance of a large lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude) were abſolutely neceſſary for theſe times, and it would honour you excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly to ſeeke for it; you may have alſo allowance, for all falſe ſlande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous invectives, if once you have gotten them Licenc'd, and Printed, ſuch as are in <hi>Walwyns Wiles;</hi> all ſuch ſhall not be doubted for lies: but a Law would be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous neceſſary, though it were never kept, you can bear with that, though we, as you ſay, cannot, but are clamouring alwayes about the Selfe-denying Ordinance: well, pray get a Law, and draw it up as large as will ſerve <hi>your ſeared Conſciences, that durſt ſubſcribe ſuch abominable ones, as that booke containeth;</hi> it being a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pities, that you, who have ever been ſo forward for the good of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, ſhould ſtay till ſome that are not of Churches, or ſome obſcure infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Churches ſhould move for it; nay, and may occaſion a greater ſtrictneſſe, then will ſerve your turne.</p>
            <p>Many conſiderations will be neceſſary in the making of it; for as you know in wraſtling, three foiles, are valued a fall: ſo it muſt be expreſt, how many mentall reſervations ſhall make a lie; how many feignings, how many times appearing as a ſpie; whether a ſpie under an oath can lie, ſo long as he intends the ſervice of his principals: how many times a man may walke and diſcourſe familiarly in diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, before it amount to a lie; how many lies a years hypocriſie amount to: that ſo, ſuch as Mr <hi>Richard Price,</hi> Mr <hi>Brandriff</hi> and the like, may be reckoned with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: and then to proportion puniſhments to offences; you have time and leiſure, and I perceive, meet together for worſe purpoſes, ſo I leave it to you.</p>
            <p>Only thus much for encouragement; <hi>Almanzar</hi> the firſt (or third) of the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>razens</hi> Emperors, made uſe of ſuch a Law, by which (above any other meanes) a mighty people were kept in great quietneſſe and proſperity, as you may read in a little Book, called the <hi>Life of Mahomet;</hi> and are we not in a low forme for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, when we are not ſo wiſe as ſuch Schoole-maſters? O miſerable Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion!</p>
            <p>But I muſt take heed what I ſay, for it ſeemes the Petition of the 11 of <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> is afreſh come into their minds, and all the circumſtances therein reckoned up, as matter of provocation to all intereſts, and of deviſion to the honeſt party; for of all Petitions, after that which was burnt, this conteined moſt particulars; and then, and long after, was that wherein the wel-affected from all parts, and Countries, did agree and center; ſo that it proved a Petition of the greateſt power of uniting, as ever was: and was by the heads, and choſen men of theſe mens friends agreed unto, to be the ſubſtance of an <hi>Agreement of the People;</hi> as Lieut: Collonel <hi>Iohn Lilburne,</hi> Mr Doctor <hi>Parker,</hi> and others can teſtifie: and yet now by this author, muſt be raiſed againſt me, as if but for me, that Petition, had never been ſeen; &amp; as if his judgement were to be valued to the blaſting of that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:44414:16"/> which received the approbation of many thouſands of the moſt cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>all friends the Parliament, and Army had throughout <hi>England:</hi> I wonder of what honeſt party, this author reckons himſelf to be; if this Petition were ſo unworthy an exaſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Petition, who did it exaſperate? if this Petition did demonſtrate my deſigne of miſchief to the honeſt party; I ſay (as he ſaies) let any mans reaſon judge impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially and determine; certainly theſe people have reſolved themſelves to be, and have contracted ſome corrupt intereſt, that the matters of that Petition now ſo much troubles them: but why this muſt fall upon my accompt, more then upon any others, that I do not ſee; only he hath undertaken to try what work his wit can make of any thing; and out of the ſtrength of his braine, preſumes he can turne my promotion of the beſt things to my diſadvantage, although (but that I will not favour his expectation with a blab) I could tell him how little I had to do in that Petition; but why ſhould I take care to ſet that man right, that cares not which way he goes, to do miſchiefe, and will not be diſſwaded? and whoſe ends are ſo unworthy, as to affright all men from Petitioning, without his, and his aſſociates allowance?</p>
            <p>I know not whether any body ſets him to this unhappy work, or whether he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiouſly undertakes it of himſelfe, but truely to me he ſeemes to be but an imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent workman to his pretended ends; for as in the former part, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> man (to my apprehenſion) ever more wounded Religion, and the honour of God and his Word, then he hath done, upon pretence of wounding me: ſo in this other part, which he pretends for the honour of the preſent Parliament; what man in the world would have made ſuch a repetition of things? trumpeting out himſelfe really ſuch things, as I am confident, he never heard from me, nor any body elſe: it hath not been my uſe to ſtir much in what is paſt; but my way hath been to propoſe a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing by of what is gone, and laying a good foundation for the time to come; that there might be no need of ſuch complaints, as he there more Rhetorically, then truly, reckons up as uttered againſt me.</p>
            <p>
               <q>As how baſely things go; what Oppreſſions, Taxations, and vexations, the poor people indure, how this poor betrayed Nation is bought and ſold; how the cutting off ſome Tyrants, do alwaies make way for more, and worſe to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed them; how nothing is done for the Common-wealth; how baſely the treaſure of the Common-wealth is embezell'd; how Parliament-men Vote mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney out of the purſes of the poor ridden people, into their owne; how they ſhare the riches of the Nation among themſelves; how to day, they Vote this Parliament-man into a great Office, and to morrow, another; and now they doe nothing for the Common-wealth, but Vote one another into places of power and profit; how that, though to abuſe, and caſt a miſt before the eyes of the people; they made a Selfe denying Ordinance, yet ſuffer no man to put it in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; how they promote their Kindred and Allies, into great places every where; if any uſe be for men in the Cuſtome houſe, in Exciſe office, or in any other places of profit, this, and that Parliament-man's friends, or brothers, or ſons, or nephewes muſt be the men; nay, Parliament-men and their allyes, have place upon place, and office upon office; as if they had ſeverall bodies, to be imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at one and the ſame time: What's become of the infinite ſum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es, the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceiveable Treaſure of the Nation; the late King's Cuſtomes, Ship money, Coat and Conduct money, Monopolies, &amp;c. were nothing to the Cuſtomes, Exciſe, Taxations, Free quarter, Sequeſtrations, Papiſts monies, Biſhops Lands, Revenues of the Crowne; beſides all the Plate and monies, lent freely by the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:44414:16"/> people, and yet nothing done: nay, how many for their zeal and good will to the State, have lent freely and bountifully, thereby beggering and undoing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and now cannot receive one peny to buy them bread, but may lie begging, petitioning, and ſtarving at their dores, and cannot be heard; nay, it may be, have nothing but courſe, hard and cruel language from them; how one Faction tears the Commonwealth, &amp; ſhare it among them one while, &amp; another another while, neither of them regarding the eaſe or grievances of the poor people all this while: And what have they done ſince this purge, and that purge? they have voted the continuance of tythes, the laying of more taxes and rates, they impriſon honeſt men, &amp;c.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe he implyes, are my ordinary diſcourſes, to the diſparagement of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and that too ſince the King's Death; for my part, I muſt deny it; and that if I ſhould have in any place, or at any time, ſpoken, or directed others to ſpeak all what he there recites, I had ſpoken what I do not know to be true; for I have ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver made it my work to take a Catalogue of the failings of Authority, but have fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently propoſed a generall remiſſion and ſecurity to all men, for what hath been paſt (as I ſaid before) without which I never expected peace, or an end of wars and miſeries: And this my back friend, Mr <hi>Arnald,</hi> may averr on my behalf; to whom I once gave a paper (upon his ſight and deſire) to that end: ſo far have I been from blowing ſuch coles as theſe, that if any ever caſt water or milk upon this wild-fire, I have done my endeavour therein.</p>
            <p>But I muſt not be what indeed I am, but what this and theſe men are pleaſed to give me out; unto whoſe ſecret ſuggeſtions, and falſe aſperſions continually whiſper'd by them at Parliament, and <hi>Derby</hi>-houſe, I impute all the hard meaſure <hi>I</hi> have found (and which, I fear, will be the undoing of me, my Wife, and Children) there being none of the Gentlemen of either place, I am certain, have any thing againſt me, but what theſe men bring; and ſome of them, I am confident, have that experience of my integrity and ingenuity in all I have done in relation to the publique, that they would do as much for my deliverance out of this affliction, as for any mans in the world.</p>
            <p>And truly, whether he wounds me or the Parliament more, in making ſuch a Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toricall recitall of ſo many particulars, as, whether true or falſe, will be apt enough to be believed in theſe ſad, complaining and diſtracted times; let any man that hath reaſon, judge.</p>
            <p>So that if he meant not to wrong the Parliament, but me, he hath over-done his work, which generally befals ſuch as take not their Conſciences along with them in what they undertake; they over-do, do, and undo, ordinarily; as you may obſerve by his ſo many firſts, ſeconds, thirds, his doubling and trebling of them, and his run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning over one and the ſame thing again and again, as if he labour'd with the diſeaſe of multiplication.</p>
            <p>But truly, when I conſider with what a continued, but ſecret malice, they have purſued me; and that all their pretended reconcilements and friendſhips, have been but counterfeit, <hi>I</hi> can impute the ſame to nothing more then emulation: for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this Parliament, I was accuſtomed to diſcourſe much with Mr <hi>Goodwins</hi> hearers, upon what they and <hi>I</hi> had heard him preach; and my character of him uſually was, that he ſpent much time (in my apprehenſion) to make plain things difficult to be underſtood, and then labour'd again to make them plain and eaſie to be underſtood; but he had ſo perplex'd them, as that he could not: this <hi>I</hi> know did ſorely trouble them, though when they fell to congregate in a Church-way, they gave me good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:44414:17"/> as needing the help of every one, whoſe conſcience (as mine did) led them out to ſtand and plead for liberty of Conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> believe they were alſo not a little troubled, that <hi>I</hi> cloſed not with them, or ſome others, in their Church-way; for ſo <hi>I</hi> once perceived by one Mr <hi>Lamb,</hi> a Linnen Draper in Cornhill; to whom <hi>I</hi> having ſold a good parcel of linnens, and taking it very kindly that he would deal with me, I would needs give him and ſome Friends with him, a cup of beer and ſugar one morning, and we were all free and chearfull: but Mr <hi>Lamb</hi> and I out-ſtaid the reſt, falling very largely into diſcourſe, he putt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng all the queſtions and doubts he had concerning my opinions; which I anſwered one by one, upon condition that he would give himſelf and me time, then, and hear me out all I had to ſay, becauſe (as I then told him) I never had received prejudice from any diſcourſe that ever paſs'd from me with ingenious men, but where they carried away things peece-meal, and by halfs: So in a moſt friendly manner he heard me, and, in concluſion, approved exceedingly of all I had ſaid, even with abundance of content and rejoycing: but when we had done, he fetches a deep ſigh, ſaying, O, Mr <hi>Walwyn,</hi> tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you had a good opinion of Churches.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwered, that I had no evil opinion of them; that rather I did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce to ſee with what amity and friendſhip they enjoyed each others ſociety in a comfortable way, aſſiſting and ſupporting one another; that I was glad they ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedly enjoyed the exerciſe of their conſciences in a way that was agreeable to their judgments; that I had made it my work, as far as I was able, to preſerve unto them, and all others, the enjoyment of that juſt liberty; it being a principle in me, that every man ought to be protected in the uſe of that wherein he doth not actually hurt another; and that were I ſatisfied in ſome particulars, I could not but joyn my ſelf to ſome ſuch ſociety; that I thought, as I was, I wanted much of that intimacy with good people which they had, but yet muſt not purchaſe it upon a doubtfull conſcience, or againſt my judgment; that I wiſh'd them all happineſſe in their way, and was not willing to diſturb any, and hop'd they would not diſturb me; hoping, that they would have as good an opinion of me, as I had of them though <hi>I</hi> did not joyn in a Church-way: and with this he then ſeemed to be very well ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</p>
            <p>And ſo we held very fair and ſerious reſpects a good while, <hi>I</hi> giving him ſome vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits at his houſe, where he would reade to me with much admiration, ſome of Mr <hi>Goodwin</hi>'s Books; the weakneſſe whereof I made ſomewhat bol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> withall (as being never uſed to flattery, or to balk my judgment) which proved a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>noli me tangere:</hi> for Mr <hi>Goodwin</hi> is the apple of their eie, and in a ſhort time, not only his familia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ceaſed, but I was even ſlandered to death from this man's mouth; no place wherever he came, but his aſperſions flew abroad; as if to blaſt my reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, had been given him in commiſſion from the whole Congregation: this was the fruit of my intimacy with him.</p>
            <p>Nor can I imagine any other reaſon why Mr <hi>Brandriff</hi> ſhould deal ſo unworthily with himſelf and me; for when we have been together, he hath diſcours'd to me much concerning his Wife, his Father, his Children, what he had done for his Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, how ingratefull they were, the manner of his trade; how, and by what means he got good ſtore of monies, in the midſt of the wars, by riſing early in mornings, and ſearching in Inns, what goods were brought to Town (indeed moſt commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and induſtriouſly) how he many times ventered to buy goods he had little ſkill in, nor knew not when he had bought them, where he was like to vent them; yet how well he ſped, with abundance of things, I will not repeat, theſe being ſufficient
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:44414:17"/> to ſhew the man, was not certainly feigned towards me ſo long a time as afterwards he pretended; only when we have been hearing Mr <hi>Goodwin</hi> together, and come from him diſcourſing, I have ſhewed ſuddenly ſome miſtakes, and weakueſſes, and drineſſes in things which Mr <hi>Goodwin</hi> had much laboured to make good, but would not endure my touchſtone; and Mr <hi>Brandriff</hi> hath been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orc'd to confeſſe as much; ſadly ſmiling and ſaying, well, what ſhall we ſay? where can we hear better? To which I would anſwer, that's not the thing, you ſee what this is.</p>
            <p>Indeed, but for this, which can be nothing but emulation, I know not any cauſe I have given them thus to perſecute me; they have thank'd me for Books I have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, as my <hi>Whiſper,</hi> and others fore-named; and for, a Book, entituled, <hi>A help to the underſtanding of Mr Pryn,</hi> which they would no nay, but it ſhould be mine, though my name was not to it; ſo good an opinion they had of my integrity: Nay, their Church diſburſed fifty ſhillings towards the printing of ten thouſand of that little Book, called, <hi>The word in ſeaſon</hi> (they then judg'd the diſperſing of Books no ſin) which Mr <hi>Batcheler</hi> can tell who was Author of, and they know well enough; ſo far were they from believing what now they ſubſcribe to; that in all times I ever oppoſed the preſent Government; but it will be found only, that I never flattered them by ſuch undue expreſſions, as, by the womb that bare you, and the paps that gave you ſuck, and the like, more ſutable to the liberty of Sycophants, then Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: Nor did I ever oppoſe any juſt authority otherwiſe then as I have oppoſed men: not to deſtroy them, but their deſtructive errours and miſ-applications of their power.</p>
            <p>Well, ye are the moſt ſtrange conditioned people that ever I met withall, the moſt inconſiſtent; walking, not by any principles, but meerly by occaſion, and as the wind turns; and I am heartily glad I have ſo nigh done with you, for I never ſhall be induced to beſtow the like pains about you again: only I have this farther to acquaint the ingenious withall concerning you, <hi>viz:</hi> that you bear your ſelves ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry high and confidently upon your ability of proving whatſoever you alleadge by way of aſperſion againſt any man: And indeed herein, I can reſemble you to none ſo properly, as to a people are called, <hi>Gypſyes</hi> (I muſt intreat pardon, if there ſeem any lightneſſe or deſpiſing in this <hi>ſimile)</hi> for if I could have found one more hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſo proper, <hi>I</hi> would not have ſtained my paper with this: but juſt ſo have I found them confederated together; if one but averr a thing, preſently there are a cloud of witneſſes; and not in a ſlighting way, but ſuch as will take their oaths of it, Upon which accompt, upon the Exchange, all their affirmatives concerning others, and there negatives concerning themſelves, are carried on; bearing down, by this one trick, all their oppoſers.</p>
            <p>And ſo they dealt in a moſt filthy ſcandall concerning an honeſt man I know ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred ſuch baſeneſſe; and which was carried all over the Town by this kind of Congregationall men: <hi>I</hi> reproving of it, and ſaying, the parry would not to put it up, but would ſeek for remedy at Law; one of them rounds me in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, If you are his Friend, adviſe him to be quiet; for I am told by as godly men as at the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> the thing will be witneſſed upon ſufficient mens oaths: whereas, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the thing was of ſo abominable a nature, as I do not believe ever was, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> be proved by witneſſes, all circumſtances of day, and light, and open ſtreet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered: And truly they are as cunning at diſperſing, as they are confident in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that the reſemblance may well hold; for generally all their aſperſions, though they are ſo vile, as, if believed, ſhall undo a man and his family, in reſpect of the loathings they will beget in all that know him: yet you ſhall ever have the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuch as
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:44414:18"/> by law you ſhall hardly ever take hold of them: ſo that they exceedingly preſume, never giving over railing and writing, that there is no poſſibility of ſilencing them: ſhame they care not for, and no prejudice can come unto them; for touch one, and touch all; all have one purſe for a common end, offenſive and defenſive; and if they ſhould by theſe courſes grow ſo odious, as that no body elſe would truſt them; their Conſederacy is ſo large, that by buying, and ſelling, and purchaſing, and lending, they are able to enrich one another, ſo as they grow to a mighty intereſt, as diſtinct almoſt as the Jews in <hi>Amſterdam;</hi> and much to the ſame ends of gain, but have greater aims of power and dominion.</p>
            <p>And <hi>I</hi> beſeech God to deliver me out of their unmercifull hands, before they yet grow greater; for I look upon my ſelf as their Priſoner, aſperſed and impriſoned, and even ruin'd by their ingratefull, Un-Chriſtian ſuggeſtions and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinations.</p>
            <p>Mr <hi>K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffin,</hi> I hear, ſince he hath ſubſcribed, <hi>Walwyns Wyles,</hi> deſires I would give him a meeting, with others he will bring with him; and if proof be not then made of the truth of thoſe things therein alleadged againſt me, effectually and ſufficiently, he will then himſelf write againſt the Book: what an offer is here? he hath ſet his name already to the Book, as a witneſſe, and publiſhed the Book (before ever he, or any man elſe ever ſpake to me of it) to my diſparagement, and undoing (were men as ready in believing, as they are in ſcandalizing) and now he offers a meeting to have thoſe falſhoods proved.</p>
            <p>Is this like the Paſtor of a Congregation of Chriſtians? Good God! what are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aln to Congregations, that they can bear with ſuch Paſtors! Truly, Mr <hi>Kiffin,</hi> although your people will not deal with you as you deſerve, I ſhall be bold to perſwade you to leave them; and take ſuch with you as are of your own mind, and colour your faces of a tauny colour, and purſue the profeſſion, you have begun the practice al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready; and ceaſe to (can't, ſhall I ſay, I even tremble to think it is no better) to deceive, I will ſay, any longer, in the name of the Lord; for God is a jealous God, and will one day recompence it.</p>
            <p>A man that looks upon theſe ſeeming Saints, no mervail if they take them for ſuch indeed, they are ſo ſolemn in their countenances, ſo frequent and ſo formall in their devotions, ſo ſad at others chearfulneſſe, ſo watchfull over others tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pping, ſo cenſorious over others failings, having a kind of diſdainfulneſſe at others, beſpeaking them in effect to ſtand farther off, I am holyer then thou; it being a great ſcruple amongſt many of them, the lawfulneſſe of playing at Cards, or the like recreation, as being a vain expence of time.</p>
            <p>Whereas all this is meer out-ſide, and but the waſhing of the out-ſide of the pot, a but appearing holy before men, to gain the repute of Godlineſſe; ſhut but the dores, and let them but be ſure of their company, and they are as other men for ſports, and jigs, and jeers, and idle jeſts and tales, and laugh and love it, and even lie down again; for if they would do thus before me, and ſome other of my Friends, what will they do when they are alone one amongſt another? Collonel <hi>Tichburn</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, at Mr <hi>Hunts</hi> houſe at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> telling ſo naſty a tale of a Scotch-man that would reach a Lord to give himſelf a vomit, crooking his fingers, and thruſting them as into one place, and then into his mouth, and down again, and up again, acting of it with ſo much art, and delight, and laughter, as that other ſolemn man, Mr <hi>Daniel Taylor,</hi> and Mr <hi>Richard Price,</hi> were ready to burſt themſelves with laughter; Mr <hi>Taylor</hi> calling out for more jeſts and ſports, being<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as he ſaid, extremely troubled with melancholly; I would he were troubled with no worſe.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:44414:18"/>
            <p>For it was but a ſlippery trick of him, to allow of all I ſaid againſt Exciſe, as an extreame burthen to Trades; and ſaying he felt it himſelfe, and was at that time in queſtion at the Office, and wiſhing it downe with all his heart; when at the very ſame time, or juſt upon it, he writes a Letter to the Commiſſioners of the Exciſe, adviſing them not to be ſo ſevere in dealing with him, for the times were like to be ſuch, as they might need the leaſt of their friends; whereas in an eminent place, he had appeared in no mean manner, in defence of the Exciſe, or to this effect; yet theſe, forſooth, muſt paſſe for the only holy, unſpotted men of the times; ſo as a man that hath but a chearfull countenance is ſcarce fit for their company, and he that ſhould be ſaid in their company to carry two faces under one hood; O what a wretch were he! but theſe it ſeemes may do any thing; and as the proverb hath it, better ſteale a horſe, then others looke over the hedge; but you muſt note, Captaine <hi>Lacy,</hi> and Mr <hi>Lamb,</hi> fellow members with Mr <hi>Taylor</hi> of Mr <hi>John Goodwins</hi> Congregation, have ſome hundreds of pounds in the Exciſe, which yeilds them good intereſt (what ere it doth the Common-wealth) and how many Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gationall mens caſes it may be, they knew better then I; and ſo Mr <hi>Daniel Taylor,</hi> had more reaſon for what he did, then he would tell every body of: theſe relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are the tenter-hooks, upon which all oppreſſions hang, and cannot get off; if they but concerne one of a Congregationall way, you draw Dunne out of the mire, and none of that way will help, but hinder you.</p>
            <p>And for Col: <hi>Tychburn's</hi> jeſt as they call'd it, and their other gibbiſh pratling, how long one had been from his Wife, and how long another; which was to me no better then catterwawling; I was wondred at I was no merrier, being ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what dumpiſh by thinking, why thoſe men ſeperated themſelves from other men; and ſadly conſidering, what a ſtroake this light eaſie people were like to have; through their ſeeming Godlineſſe, in the greateſt affaires of the Common-wealth, as ſoone after was, and hath been ſeen.</p>
            <p>But its well knowne, I, and all that were with me, were ſo far from telling theſe things any where to their diſparagement, or ſo much as ſpeaking of it, that we agreed it ſhould not be knowne, leſt we ſhould break thoſe rules of ſociety, which require honeſt men, not to talke to any mans diſcredit, whatever befell in company, where no evill to any man was intended; and truly, but that now theſe men ſeeme to ſtretch themſelves and to walke on tiptoe, not only upon my ruines, but without all tenderneſſe of compaſſion, towards my dear Wife and Children; yea, and inſult over our more dear Cauſe, and our Countries Liberties, bearing downe all upon an opinion of their godlineſſe, and our licentiouſneſſe, which we more abhor then themſelves; theſe ſtories had been buried in the grave of ſilence, but as they have borne themſelves, not regarding our manifeſtation, but deſpiſing and jeering of it; and by their moſt uncharitable Book, raiſing up a whole legion of ſcandals and ſlanders againſt me; a neceſſity was upon me, to ſhew theſe men as they are not as they labour by hypocriſie to appear unto the world.</p>
            <p>I have onely one requeſt to this ſort of men, and I have done with them; and that is, That they would agree among themſelves, to wear ſome very viſible and remarkable thing, either upon their breaſts, or in their ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts, in that company where they reſolve to be ſincere; and to make no perſidious uſe of that meeting, or converſation, whilſt they weare it, and to keep it in their pockets, or concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, when they intend to deceive; and it will be neceſſary in your next Book, to publiſh what this note ſhall be, that all men may expect it, and accordingly keep you company or not, and know how to behave themſelves in their converſing with
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:44414:19"/> you; in the obſervation whereof alſo, you muſt adviſe all thoſe that have been uſed to deceive; eſpecially thoſe that have profeſt to have kept me company, purpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to turn all I did to my prejudice; that they be very exact and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>acere in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation thereof, for otherwiſe it will come to nothing; and no body will know where to have you, or how to confer with you.</p>
            <p>It hath been others caſes, who have uſed over much diſſimulation, as <hi>Lewis</hi> the 11th of <hi>France,</hi> who in his tranſactions with <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> conclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Peace, Truce, and Articles upon Oathes; and nothing provin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of force to hold him; neither oathes, nor ſacraments, nor execrations, nor covenants, nor any ſuch bonds as ſhould hold inviolable all contracts amongſt men; in concluſion, he diſcovers the image of St. <hi>Claud,</hi> which he continually wore in his hart; and after he had offered any other obligation, in a thing he was ſuſpected not to intend, or keep; he urging him to ſwear by that St. <hi>Claud,</hi> he refuſed; as not daring to break faith up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that oath; this was ſomething yet; and truly, when you ſhall conſider to what a paſs you have brought your ſelves, you cannot but conclude upon ſome ſuch courſe.</p>
            <p>And having thus turned your inſides outwards, though with unpleaſing paines to himſelf, and much trouble to the ingenious Reader (for I was hopefull I had done for ever with this kind of work, when our manifeſtation and Agreement of the People was once abroad) you may without ſpectacles, read in your own hearts, written in Capitall letters, what you through a great miſtake intended to me, and my friends, in the firſt enterance of your Book: namely, <q>That the greateſt hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, is often palliated with the moſt ſpecious pretences of the plaineſt ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and the chiefeſt uſe that ſome men make of Religion, and the language there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is (after the ſimilitude of Satan with our firſt parents) to mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of over credulous and flexible men, and then to cheat them, under a guilded bait of their ſeeming good, unto ſuch actions, that are moſt conducible to their certaine miſery: If this be not true of you, and due to you it hath no true owners in the world.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo I have done with you all, and all your Wiles; and henceforth, he that is filthy, let him be filthy ſtill; and he that is ignorant, let him be ignorant ſtill; he that is ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ouly partiall in his Conſcience, as after this my Juſt Defence, to believe your ſlanders of me, let him remaine ſo ſtill; and he that through a perverſe igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, ſhall henceforth doubt my integrity, let him remaine ignorant ſtill: I would gladly be free from this Reſtraint, becauſe I fear it will prove prejudiciall to many more beſides my ſelfe, if not already; and I truſt, God will open ſome juſt way; however, I have peace within, becauſe in all that hath befallen me; my will is not to harme any man, nor to diſhonour God; affliction being ſtill to me, a better choice then ſin.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>William Walwyn.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:44414:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
